This is George Lucas.
I'm the executive producer
and writer of Return of the Jedi.
I'm Dennis Muren,
visual effects supervisor at ILM.
Hi. I'm Carrie Fisher.
And this is Ben Burtt, sound designer
and supervising sound editor...
and also rerecording mixer on...
Return of the Jedi.
LUCAS: Richard Marquand
was the director of the film.
He'd done some great suspense films
and was really good
at working with actors.
Eye of the Needle was the film
I'd seen that he had done
that impressed me most.
It was really nicely done,
had a lot of energy and suspense.
These movies, by this time, had gotten
to be more like television shows.
The hierarchy in the way
a television show works, creatively,
is very much different than
the way it works on a motion picture.
The executive producer pretty much
is the overall creative overseer
of the project...
and comes up with the ideas for
the scripts and works on the scripts.
And the directors just try
to fulfill the obligation
of getting it on the screen.
Where, mostly in feature films, a lot of
the creative control lies in the director.
It's not so much today as it was then,
but I've discovered over the years that
it's easy to collaborate with directors...
if there's mutual respect
about what you're doing...
and a kind of general
agreement on the sensibility
of where you're going with something...
or what kind of a film it's gonna be
or what the tone of it is gonna be.
If you can agree on those sorts of things
in the beginning before you start off,
it works out pretty well.
I had a great time working
with Richard Marquand.
He was a very talented director
and a very nice guy.
He'd never done
a film of this scale before,
with special effects
and all that sort of thing...
so, just as on Empire Strikes Back...
I was there to assist and help...
and sort of give my expertise.
These films are so huge...
that it's really hard
to do it by yourself.
I mean, you really need to have a lot of
people to support you in all the areas.
Fortunately in this one,
especially in the art department
and a lot of the other departments,
we were using the same group
that we'd used before.
In special effects,
it was the same group.
So it was easier for me
to shorthand with a lot of people,
and that became
a real asset for Richard...
because I could say, "Don't worry
about that. We'll take care of it."
A lot of the technical complications
and everything he didn't even
have to worry about.
He just focused on, you know, getting
the performances out of the actors...
and making sure
the story got told on the set.
We had that cooperative relationship...
where if I said, "Just do it like this
and don't worry about it,"
he was curious about what
was gonna happen,
but he didn't spend a lot of time...
trying to reinvent the wheel or say,
"No, I don't wanna do it that way."
Because he'd say, "Look, if this is
the way you do this, it's much easier.
Let's just do this 'cause
that'll all be a matte painting anyway."
It's very easy, especially at this stage
in special effects
where it was relatively new,
to get hung up trying to figure out how
things were gonna actually come out.
The only way you ever really know
is having gone through it a few times.
Then you can sort of anticipate
where everything's gonna be.
A film like this operates on a lot of
faith. The actors have to have faith,
and in this case
the director had to have a lot of faith
that it would actually come together...
and all the missing pieces would
mysteriously appear in post-production.
BURTT: The footsteps for Darth Vader
as he comes down the ramp...
were recorded
in underground tunnels...
in the Marin Headlands
near the Golden Gate Bridge.
There's a network
of underground military tunnels...
which are actually
closed off from the public.
But back at the time
that Jedi was done...
you could squeeze through
one of the old, rusty gates...
and go deep down
into the catacombs...
into the headlands
around the Golden Gate Bridge.
Gary Summers and I took our
tape recorder and some heavy boots...
and some other props
and we went down into these tunnels
and did a lot of the footsteps-
echoey, heavy footsteps
for Darth Vader.
Along the way,
we also got some great
rusty doors opening and closing,
which were used for various sounds
of ramps and gates...
and things that happen in Jedi.
There's a lot of machinery
in every Star Wars film,
and we could never collect enough
squeaky doors and electric motors...
in order to make up all the different
sounds that occur in the spaceships...
and all the places that we go.
LUCAS: It's the final chapter...
of the original concept for Star Wars.
There were a lot of things that were...
added into this one
because of the fact that...
by the time I got down this far
from the original script...
the story had become pretty thin
and I had to fill in a lot of blanks.
This first whole sequence
with Jabba the Hutt...
was more an afterthought
than anything else.
The original story was really
about the primitive society...
overcoming the Empire at the end and...
Luke managing to redeem his father.
The part of the script this actually
represented in the very first outline,
where I had this whole story outlined,
was like the last 20 pages of the script.
So I had to come up with
another 100 pages of stuff...
to fill in the blanks
and make it work...
because Han Solo had become
such a popular character.
And I thought it'd be fun
to go back to Tatooine.
And I wanted to deal
with Jabba the Hutt,
which kinda got lost
in the process.
He was a much bigger character
in the original script.
A lot of those things motivated me
to go in this direction...
and spend the first quarter of the movie
back on Tatooine with Jabba the Hutt.
BURTT: In Jedi, we had quite a bit
of Huttese language to create.
This was the language
spoken by Jabba the Hutt
and all the people in his palace.
It starts out with this little eye robot
that pops out the door.
We used the talents of Larry Ward,
who was a linguist.
He was an expert at speaking
many different languages,
and he helped me develop the Huttese
language back on New Hope.
In fact, Larry had done the voice
for Greedo the bounty hunter.
But Larry's biggest contribution
to this film...
was by doing the voice
of Jabba the Hutt.
LUCAS: As with all these movies,
the original intent...
was to make this a very full
and exotic environment...
that these movies would take place in.
And so, each film we tried to
push the envelope a little bit further...
in terms of unique characters...
and take it into
a more visually exciting...
and unusual area.
The problem always was,
to do that is very difficult.
And especially
before digital technology,
if you had to have
exotic robots and things,
they were mostly marionettes...
or stop-motion
or something of that ilk.
So we were just pushing the limits
of cinematic technology at that point...
to just get strange creatures.
The first two films
were pretty light on creatures.
We had a little bit in the cantina
in Episode IV,
and in Episode V we put most of
our effort and focus on Yoda...
trying to get Yoda to become real.
Once we managed
to make Yoda work and become real,
then we, on this film,
tried to expand that idea...
and make Jabba and the rancor...
and the people in Jabba's court-
the pig guards, the strange droids-
to make it
a much more exotic environment
and use them more.
We barely, barely, barely were able to
put together
the very first cantina scene.
We shot it, then had to go reshoot it and
make more creatures, and reshoot it...
and constantly trying
to bring it up to the level that
I had originally hoped it would be.
And so each one of these
kind of exotic scenes-
there's a huge amount of work
behind every single idea...
to try to get to the level where
you can create an alien environment...
on the level of just
not having to think about it.
It's one thing to do a creature.
It's another thing to do 35 or 40
or 50 creatures in each scene.
MUREN: This is Jabba the Hutt,
who was designed, I believe,
by Phil Tippett
here at ILM when he was here.
We had quite a large creature shop,
actually, at ILM at the time...
building a lot of characters
for Jedi here.
Then they got shipped over to England
where they were shot.
It was a great big rubber creature
with a number of people behind it,
inside of it, and moving around.
LUCAS: There's a dwarf in the tail...
and then a couple guys
on remote controls
running the tongue and the eyes.
They have to rehearse
and rehearse and rehearse
to get all the movements right...
so that he'll
do the right thing 'cause they're all
trying to coordinate their moves.
The group came mostly
out of Jim Henson's group,
which is probably the best
in terms of just sheer talent and skills...
of working on puppets and puppeting...
especially as everything has advanced
to more
remote-controlled puppeteering.
They were the ones that led
most of that technology.
MUREN: Some of these little characters-
This little character here
is a little rod puppet, I believe,
and some mechanics inside of it to
make it look spindly and kind of mobile.
With computer graphics,
you can do a lot more...
but in those days,
we were pretty limited
to the motions that we could do
with these characters.
BURTT: To give Jabba
the deepest and heaviest sound,
we took Larry's voice and we
pitched it almost an octave lower
than his natural voice.
And then we ran the voice
through a subharmonic generator...
and it gave his voice
a very booming sound,
a very heavy sound.
And then, while he spoke,
a movement track was created,
which was really
just cheese casserole.
Running your hands around
in a bowl of cheese casserole...
gave it a smooshy, kind of moist feeling
for Jabba's movements...
and a slurpiness to his voice.
But also we took a wet towel...
that had sort of been
thrown in the mud-
You take that wet towel and work with it
inside the bottom of a garbage can...
such that the sound is kinda contained
and has a little bit of a quick echo to it.
Working your hands on the towel
to give gritty, sliding sounds,
and also combining with
the cheese casserole,
were used to underscore
all of Jabba's talking and movements.
I always found that with these-
really, essentially a large puppet,
that you needed to get
some kind of grit,
some kind of subtle noise into it
when he spoke...
in order to make it seem
more present.
Those of us on the crew
almost always take turns...
doing incidental voices in the film.
The interrogator robot-
the voice was performed
by the director, Richard Marquand.
We ran his voice through a circuit
called a ring modulator,
which gave it kind of a monotonic,
electronic quality to it.
I got tortured in this film
doing the voice for the robot
having his feet burned off.
This brings up a serious issue of,
do robots feel pain? Well, I guess so.
No! No! No!
Aaahh!
The whole scene of Oola dancing...
has gone through several different
evolutionary changes.
There was originally some music done
for the first release of the film...
music which we actually recorded
at Sprocket Systems.
The lyrics were written by one of
our engineers named Annie Arbogast,
who had her own punk rock band.
I worked with her, advising her
on how to make it sound like Huttese.
But she did the original voice
and wrote the lyrics.
But then years later, when the film
was re-released in a special edition,
a whole new piece of music was written
when they added
all the digital characters...
and, you know, really elaborated
the whole scene.
LUCAS: A lot of these things
went through a lot of incarnations.
The singer, originally, was
a marionette we could barely move...
and really couldn't do
what I had wanted.
Some of the other characters
who were more static
were able to come off pretty well,
but Jabba can't really move
in this one-he's stuck on a slab.
The piano player and some
of those people are stuck on slabs
because they're puppets.
So it's as you push
the technology forward
you're able to get the creatures...
suddenly to walk or raise their arms
or have expressions on their faces.
And all that took years and years
and a lot of experimentation...
and technical advances to just be able
to get an alien character to be real.
In this particular case,
you know, make the tongue work.
[LAUGHS] Or the eyes work-
That was like a major breakthrough...
to be able to make eyelids
move up and down
and eyes move back and forth...
and the tongue go in and out
and the lips be relatively in sync.
I'm still amused by people
that somehow think...
that when you use cyber-technology,
or digital technology, in movies...
that suddenly it's... fake.
But when you look at a scene in here,
like Jabba's palace,
now there's some
digital characters in here,
but they're no more or less fake
than all the other characters
that are in here.
I mean, is a digital character more fake
than a big, fat rubber character?
[CHUCKLES]
I mean, there's nothing real here at all.
It's hard to say that
a rubber character has more integrity
than a digital character.
What I try to do is just make
the characters become believable...
so they look realistic enough to where
you have a suspension of disbelief...
and accept them as characters,
not as tricks, which is what they all are.
BURTT: The voice of Boushh-
Of course, it's Princess Leia in disguise,
but when she first appears we used
a different voice for the character.
The character was actually
voiced by Pat Welsh.
She was the woman
who was the principal voice...
of ET the Extra-Terrestrial.
I'd worked on ET,
and we had recorded her voice.
She was an elderly woman, retired,
never had acted
in any films before.
I had run into her at a photo store
in San Anselmo, California,
while she was buying film.
I heard her voice,
and her voice was
very interesting and unusual...
in that, to some extent, you couldn't
tell whether it was male or female.
One of the keys in doing alien voices...
is always to come up with a voice...
in which the audience
cannot immediately tell
whether it's male or female...
or old or young, so they don't link it up
with a familiar human being.
So, when you find voices like that...
that have that ambiguous quality
about them,
they're so useful
in these fantasy films.
Well, Pat had a voice like that,
and I just asked her,
"Do you want to be
the voice of an alien?"
And she looked at me
and she didn't even-didn't flinch
or call the police or anything.
She said-
[IMITATING PAT] "Okay. I'll try it."
So we recorded her
and worked with her over the years.
We became good friends and used her
on occasion for specialty voices.
LUCAS: Lando moved through
into this film...
primarily by my decision to focus
the beginning of this movie
on Han Solo.
Since they were pals, it was natural
that Lando would be one...
to try to redeem himself
and be there to help rescue him...
and redeem his reputation
at the same time.
Ultimately, in the original
original script...
it was mostly Luke,
the emperor and Darth Vader...
were the key elements along
with what, in the original script,
was a bunch of Wookiees.
It was a Wookiee planet.
But since I had fallen in love
with the Wookiee so much...
when I made Episode IV I decided
to make the co-pilot a Wookiee,
which meant he was
technologically advanced.
The whole concept originally
was that the people that overthrew
the Empire were not technological.
So I had to reinvent
a half-sized Wookiee.
BURTT: We always get a lot of mileage
out of Dumpsters in these films-
banging into Dumpsters,
slamming the lids on Dumpsters.
The carbon block
in which Han is encased...
when it falls on the floor, it's the sound
of a big garbage Dumpster...
recorded out in front of my home
to give it the sense of weight
and a metallic quality.
MUREN: The shot of Han
breaking out of this carbon thing,
whatever it is he's in,
was pretty tough.
It was, uh-What you're seeing
is actually a wax figure of Han,
of the real casting that was made,
but of wax, animated,
cut away one frame at a time with a
bright light on the inside, shot in smoke.
So it was a pretty bizarre thing
to figure out just how to get him to look
like this thing was peeling off of him.
And we did it with, again-with sort
of revealing bright light on the inside,
which makes absolutely no sense.
And it's been copied
in many, many films afterwards...
when they've had somebody
sort of covered with something...
and it's showing it having to peel off.
It's an interesting way to do it, sort of
as though it's glowing on the inside.
But there's no logic to it.
LUCAS: The Han Solo journey...
is a continuation of the motif
of death and rebirth,
which is the overall central theme
of this whole series...
in relationship to Darth Vader...
coming out of his evil hibernation...
and being reborn as Anakin Skywalker.
He's put to sleep,
which is a common device,
especially in fairy tales,
but also in mythological terms too,
of going into
a state of suspended animation.
And then usually
you come out rejuvenated.
Sometimes it's the equivalent of
going down to the netherworld...
and coming back enlightened.
In this particular case,
he was just put to sleep.
Ho-ho-ho-ho-ho!
What's that?
BURTT: When Jabba and his minions laugh,
it's a real combination
of human laughter
plus other animal sounds like hippos...
and hyenas and other things we've
recorded or collected over the years...
all blended together to give
a whole range of alien laughter.
LUCAS: The difficulty
of these scenes in Jabba's palace,
especially with Jabba,
is that Jabba can't move.
I didn't have the technology at that time
to make him move around,
so whenever I had to do a scene
I had to plop him down somewhere...
and then stage the scene around him,
which made for
this inconvenient staging
in the revelation scene here...
of him having to be
behind a curtain.
Otherwise, he could just come
through the door,
which is what
I would have preferred.
But these were the days when most of
the creatures were nailed to the floor.
BURTT: Sometimes you can
create the ambience
for a place in a very simple way.
A lot of the sound in the detention cell
is dripping water,
but really it was just taking
an eyedropper...
and doing single drops into
a little coffee cup full of water...
and then putting that in
an echo chamber, several tracks of it.
And out of that comes just a subtle
off screen "plink-plink" of the water.
But it makes it seem like a dank and
leaky kind of subterranean place,
and it adds a coloration
to the environment.
LUCAS: The advantage
we have in these films...
is that it takes about 10 years
to get through the trilogy.
So Mark was pretty young
when we did the first one...
and he was
a much more mature individual...
by the time we reached this film.
The same thing with Carrie.
With Harrison it didn't show up so much
'cause he started out, he was over 30.
But Carrie started out at 19,
and Mark was in his 30s
by the time he finished.
So it allowed him to use
a lot more of his maturity,
not only in the natural
telling of the story,
when he becomes more mature,
but he actually was more mature
as an actor and as an individual.
So I think a lot of
his naive boyishness...
that existed in A New Hope
just naturally...
drifted away by the time
we got to this film.
He was a much more serious person.
BURTT: Another local performer
from the Bay Area
who provided
some important voices in this film...
for our alien characters
was Erik Bauersfeld.
And he provided the voice
for Bib Fortuna.
He has a refined,
almost a mild British accent,
which gave Bib an unusual sense
of dignity despite his appearance.
Master.
Oohh!
FISHER: George got me up
to San Francisco and showed me...
a picture of this bathing suit...
to frighten me into exercise, I think.
He succeeded.
This is the other thing, too,
that they wanted-
"Do not have any lines
on the side of you."
You know,
there's no wrinkles on your body.
So there can be no line,
like I'd been bending in half or-
So I can do that, right there.
Remain motionless,
sit up really unnaturally straight...
and do not speak at all.
That's it. No "hello. ""Hey, hi! Look!
I'm in a bathing suit made of iron!"
LUCAS: We hadn't done
a monster per se in these.
We had the snow monster
on Empire Strikes Back,
but in a lot of cases we were just
moving through various genre motifs...
of fantasy and science fiction
and having a little bit of fun.
BURTT: The growls and the roars...
of the rancor beast
were derived from a very small animal.
It was actually a pet dachshund...
owned by a neighbour of mine.
Despite the fact that
it was a cute little dog,
it had a certain vicious streak in it.
And I went over one day...
and recorded this dachshund as
it growled and hissed and got angry,
and we took that sound
and pitched it down much lower.
Pal was a dangerous little old guy,
but he made a good rancor beast.
MUREN: This is a hand puppet...
with Phil Tippett's arm-
someone's arm up in it...
and hand controlling the head up there
with some mechanics inside of it.
It was probably about
15, 16 inches high...
and the arms are controlled internally,
and going straight out of the
elbows to the back,
which we kept very, very dark.
The eyes, which were so important
to this, are actually ball bearings.
The only way you could really
ever focus on it being living...
was to look at the eyes,
and the regular eyes
we made for it didn't show up,
so we just got the shiniest little eyes
we could get
so you would recognise it
as being a living thing.
And we took this approach,
as opposed to stop-mo or something,
as a way of saving money.
And we could do this pretty quick-
we shot the whole sequence
probably in-
Once we figured out how to do it,
I would just have guessed
a couple weeks,
which really wasn't too bad.
The rancor was in
the little miniature set.
The lighting effect, the smoke effect
was all done in the camera.
The only time we did
any other work to the shot
was if we had to put Luke into it.
So it was really
fairly straightforward to shoot.
It took a lot of takes-sometimes
we'd be up to 60 or 70 takes on it.
Sometimes we shot backwards.
Sometimes we shot
the scenes at different speeds-
high speed or normal speed.
Anything to get it away from
that sort of familiar Muppet look
we're all used to seeing.
But the problem is, you could never
get a wide view of it
because there were no legs
that you could ever really see.
Except we did leg shots,
but you couldn't really see it
when you saw the body...
because that's where
you would see, you know,
Phil's elbow or something down there.
The drool helped make it
look kinda creepy.
You know. 'Cause you're like,
"Just stay away from that thing."
And I think it was, you know,
sort of successful.
It suffered from what any of these
sort of robotic or hand puppets
tend to suffer from, in my point of view-
is they just don't have quite
the performance that you'd like to have.
'Cause you're so, so limited because
you're working with such problems
to try to get the thing to even move.
And one of the great things
that's come with computer graphics is...
that the performance is as good
as your imagination is,
so you can make the things
look much, much more interesting...
and their performance much more
elaborate and much more fun to watch.
LUCAS: I like the idea that
everybody loves somebody.
Even though this was the worst big,
horrible monster
you could possibly imagine,
his keeper loved him.
[CHUCKLES] And he
probably loved his keeper.
BURTT: Another one of our favourite
voice talents in the Bay Area...
is a guy named Ernie Fosselius.
He was most famous for doing
the film Hardware Wars,
a spoof of Star Wars many years ago.
But Ernie would come in whenever
we needed a good comic voice.
He did a great job of doing the voice of
the rancor trainers. He did both of them.
I remember telling Ernie to kind of
take the approach that it's Stan Laurel...
with that kind of whimpery cry.
Ernie's the kind of guy
that can practically imitate anything.
Ernie created a really funny moment
with that character.
LUCAS: Another aspect of these films
that sometimes gets lost...
is that these films
are vaguely light-hearted...
in terms of the fact they don't
take themselves that seriously.
They try to be very realistic
and everything,
but mostly it's to have
a rip-roaring adventure...
and a good time.
Sometimes people try to put more
into them than should be there...
or write them off
as of no consequence,
but the reality, I think,
is somewhere in the middle.
Again, with this movie we got a chance
to expand the universe a bit,
see more Banthas than just one or two,
see them in their natural environment.
There's so little time in these movies
to show the environments...
because we're really
pushing the story all the time.
It's great when you get
another opportunity
to push the camera over here and say,
"Oh, look what's over there."
MUREN: This is the barge sequence-
one of the sequences
Richard Edlund supervised.
It was a pretty tough sequence.
Looks pretty neat.
The backgrounds, I believe,
were all shot in Yuma, Arizona.
The ship were primarily models.
Sometimes some of
the little transporter ones on the side
were about two feet wide...
and the main barge was about
six feet long, something like that,
shot against bluescreen
and combined with the background.
Then there
was bluescreen photography, also,
shot on the stage here,
where the actors are shot blue at ILM
It's very hard to get this-
It was in those days, especially,
to get anything to look like it was
really sunlight when it was shot indoors.
And to pull the mattes of fin this,
with all the hair,
was particularly difficult.
BURTT: We sent a sound crew
out into the dunes...
while these scenes were being shot.
The main thing we got was sand
in our equipment. [CHUCKLES]
It was so windy, so much blowing sand,
that it was actually quite dangerous...
with all the gear
that we took down there.
And we ended up actually
not spending too much time on the set...
getting sand in our equipment,
but rather we went over
to a local naval air station...
and recorded jets
practicing landing and takeoff...
and got a lot of really great sounds
which became the basis...
for a lot of the speeder bikes
later in the film.
FISHER: We had, daily,
stuntmen break things.
I would come on the set
and there'd be...
this kind of... silence...
that you know
means something bad.
Dave Tomblin, who was a fantastic guy-
He was the first AD.
You know,
the walkie-talkie would crackle...
and you'd hear Tomblin say
in the cockney-
[IMITATING COCKNEY ACCENT]
"George, we're talking about two men
might have a sprained ankle.
Might have a broken leg."
Silence while they're waiting
to find out from the nurse.
And then you'd go back
to the motel...
and these very jovial guys, who have
had much worse happen to them,
would be sitting by the pool,
with casts here and there.
It was tough.
It was a tough stunt.
BURTT: I remember making the sound of Luke
bouncing off the end of the plank...
by just snapping a ruler
on the edge of a desk-a wooden ruler.
Something I learned
in fifth grade, actually.
You can make a great sound
by twanging a ruler
on the edge of your desk.
Of course, you get in trouble
with the teacher, as I did.
But it provided me with an idea later on
for a quick sound effect
when I needed it.
LUCAS: In the case of Boba Fett's death,
had I known he was gonna
turn into such a popular character,
I probably would have made it
a little bit more exciting.
Boba Fett was just
another one of the minions,
another one of the bounty hunters
and bad guys.
But he became such
a favourite of everybody's.
For having such a small part,
he had a very large presence.
And now that his history has been told
in the first trilogy,
it makes it even more of a misstep...
that we wouldn't make more
out of the event of his defeat.
Because most people
don't believe he died anyway.
I had contemplated putting in an extra
shot where he climbs out of the hole,
but I figured
it doesn't quite fit, in the end.
The main character, ultimately,
that dies in this scene is Jabba the Hutt.
As much as some people
hate the cute little Ewoks,
they love the relationship
between Princess Leia and the slug.
FISHER: He was made of Styrofoam,
I believe,
and they asked me
if I wanted a stunt double to kill him.
And I said, "Really, really not.
I really, really wanna kill him myself."
BURTT:
The battle with the Sarlacc monster...
was one of the last scenes
that we mixed in the film,
because I had gone through
a lot of editorial changes...
and there were different
versions of it...
kind of each week
as we were getting later and later
into the post-production schedule.
It was a very challenging
sequence editorially...
because, typical with
a Star Wars action sequence,
there were so many different
characters involved,
all with their own simultaneous stories.
And to sort it out, and to keep the flow
of action clear and continuous...
there was quite a bit
of re-cutting of this scene.
In fact, it was scored once
in London by Johnny Williams...
and then the sequence was recut
so many times after that...
that they had to go back
and re-score it...
with a different cue of music.
LUCAS: I'm not sure we ever really
did it as well as we could have.
But when you have so many
different pieces of action...
that are supposed to be happening
at exactly the same moment,
you get into a very complex
piece of cinema,
which is editing things together
that you want people to read...
but you don't want to dwell
on them for so long...
that it drags down
a simultaneous moment.
I think there's always
a kind of super-reality...
that's created in a moment like this
where you're stretching time...
and hoping
that it doesn't look like that.
This is something Steven Spielberg
is very accomplished at.
The best project I ever worked on
where that happened...
is in Raiders of the Lost Ark
under the Flying Wing.
It's exactly like this sequence...
where you got a truck full of gas
and some guys loading the truck.
Then you got a fight.
And then you got a pilot.
Then you got people
coming from the outside.
Then the truck catches on fire.
Then it's going toward the airplane.
Then the girl gets trapped
in the airplane.
It's very similar to this.
In that case I think it's done
as well as it can ever be done.
But in this case we did it
as well as we could, but...
I always had this nagging feeling
that we could have done it better.
It's a very delicate balance of having
the audience be able to follow it...
and not having it look corny.
BURTT: The explosion of Jabba's barge...
was probably one of the bigger
and more prolonged explosions
that we've put in the films.
Everything was thrown into it.
Probably the kitchen sink
was thrown into it.
We had several explosions,
a lot of fire.
And there was sounds of rockets
we had recorded.
And we used that for the sounds
of the debris going by camera.
We had gone once to a house
in Petaluma, California
that was being torn down.
All the furniture and fittings
were in the house...
and they said we could do anything
we wanted in this house.
So, I spent an entire day there.
We dubbed the place "Junk Heaven"...
because we went around
smashing appliances,
breaking windows,
throwing things down the stairs,
taking dressers, furniture,
tumbling it out second-story windows.
Opening up kitchen cabinets
and smashing dishes,
throwing things around.
Since it was all done in a place,
it sounded real.
It wasn't like a Foley stage where it
sometimes can be acoustically artificial.
What you want is that kind of
spontaneity about it so it's not perfect.
MUREN: There was more of everything.
There's more spaceships.
There's more characters.
The docking bays that
the ships land in are bigger.
There's a shot that was reused
from Empire.
And as the ships go in,
you see there's a lot more
than you would have seen
in the earlier films.
And a lot more detail inside.
Just more, more-Bigger.
So you get a sense that
the battle is on a massive scale.
And the docking bay here-
Every one of these shows
has a docking bay.
And they all have
reflective floors on them.
This is the biggest one, being
the last of the first three movies.
And pretty neat.
And all these characters here-
It sort of gives you an idea
what George was thinking...
when he got to Phantom Menace,
what the scale of that film would be.
He was really building it up to
just really huge, huge epic proportions.
See, in the background of these shots,
they actually probably had...
two or three dozen actors
and they would populate them
as much as they could.
Then we would fill in the rest,
either with paintings
or replicating them
and moving them around.
LUCAS: The emperor's coming
to visit the Death Star,
so it was like a big parade of
all of their weaponry and their troops.
It's like May Day in Russia.
In terms of a display of force, this
is as big as it has been at this point.
I was able to actually...
get a more cosmic view of the galaxy
by bringing the emperor into this...
who, even though he's sort of
the overlord of the universe,
is always in the background
of the movies.
In this one, I had the opportunity
to bring him into the forefront...
because it ultimately becomes
a confrontation...
between Vader and the emperor,
which is in the background
of Episodes IV and V...
but very much in the foreground
in this film.
Because that's what
the real conflict is.
The real conflict is with the real
evil master who is the emperor.
And he's referred to,
but we never really get to know him.
One of the advantages
of being in the third act...
is that you get to
tie up all of the loose ends.
But one of the problems you have
in the third act...
is that you have to
tie up all the loose ends.
The story is pretty much dictated
by everything that's gone before it...
and it's really a matter of how well you're
able to fit in all the resolutions...
and keep the story going forward.
That's usually what ties you up here...
'cause you end up
with too many things to try to solve...
and not enough time to do it in.
In coming back to see Yoda,
we have to figure out Luke's training...
and the fact that he never
finished his training...
and that obviously now he's got
a big question he wants answered.
There is a point where the hero has
to be left alone on his own two feet...
without anybody there to help him.
And you can sort of have him
be in a different place or something.
But at some point you have to say, now
all the props have been taken away...
and he has to face
the evil monster alone.
In this case, this scene establishes that
the evil monster is actually his father...
and he's gonna have to do it
on his own
and that he's not
really equipped to do it,
that he was too impatient,
he didn't finish his studies
and now he's gonna be half-trained...
to face a difficult
physical and emotional challenge.
Then I am a Jedi.
Oh! [COUGHING]
Not yet.
One thing remains-
Vader.
When I did the end of the last movie,
The Empire Strikes Back,
one of the issues that came up...
in terms of my concern
about how kids especially...
would take Darth Vader revealing
that he is Luke's father...
was most of the psychologists
said that most kids would just deny it
and say it's not true.
So, I had to reaffirm
in the audience's mind...
and in Luke's mind that it is true,
and now he has to deal with it.
Yoda, I must know.
Going into this movie,
I had to assume that at least
half of the people didn't believe it.
So I had to make it a true thing
that had happened.
Traditionally, in the original
long version of the script...
this is where Obi-Wan Kenobi dies
and leaves Luke alone.
There's always an advantage
to the third film...
in both of these trilogies,
the Star Wars trilogies,
which is that it starts out
with a young boy, naive youth,
and by the time we get to the third film
he's an experienced warrior,
he's matured into his full self...
and therefore he's always
a much more interesting character.
Because he's richer,
and he's ready to take on the world...
and his final challenge.
It's one of the things, also,
why the third chapter...
or the third act of a play
is more interesting...
because the first one
you introduce the characters,
the second, you introduce the problem
and the third
you get to resolve everything.
And this being the third part,
it has all the resolutions
of all the various problems...
that had been developed
in the first two films.
The center of the movie
is a lot of exposition.
It's a lot of explaining
what has happened...
and why things are
the way they are.
In this particular case,
there's a whole issue of Luke's sister...
and, you know,
the fact that they were twins,
which is an element
that has to be revealed...
which comes in later in terms of...
who is the "other" that was
talked about in Empire Strikes Back...
and how could that person
become as powerful as Luke?
Well, if they're twins,
then if she were trained and...
she has the same abilities Luke has,
that becomes an important issue,
especially in terms of resolving
all the love triangles
that have been going on.
BURTT: I had the opportunity
to go to London...
for the filming of Return of the Jedi...
to supervise any sound recording
that was being done on the set,
and also to gather sound effects
while I was there...
and help develop the languages
for the Ewoks...
and many of the people
in Jabba's palace.
I remember going on the set
when they weren't filming.
They were off on
some other set that day.
But Jabba the Hutt, the big puppet,
was sitting there
empty on the set all by itself.
I crawled up inside
with my tape recorder...
and recorded the little motors,
the little servomotors...
which made his eyeballs
move back and forth.
And we got a lot of mileage
out of those little motors.
The sound of the thermal detonator
which Boushh holds in his hand.
Those little motors-some of those
are from the actual eyeball motors...
that were inside the Jabba puppet.
Return of the Jedi
was the first mix...
that we did entirely
in Northern California.
The previous two episodes were
edited and sound designed up north,
but we took all the materials
to Hollywood...
where we had a lot of talented people
at Goldwyn Studios...
help us put it together
and do the final mix.
But when Jedi came along
we had for the first time
our own complete mixing facility...
in San Rafael, California.
Therefore we were able to exercise...
almost a complete technical and
creative control over the soundtrack.
It was a new experience for all of us.
Gary Summers and I
mixed this film-
and I think it really was the first
feature film we ever mixed.
I think this was really the first film
which was technically watched over
by Tom Holman...
and ultimately what became
the THX and TAP program.
There was a great deal
of engineering expertise...
that went into watching over
just the technical specifications
for doing the sound mix for this film.
Normally you mix a film...
from the beginning to the end
in the order that the scenes occur.
But because this film
was being put together...
when we started the mix
of the movie, the final mix,
we actually began work
in the middle of the movie.
We started with reel five.
And then, later, we went back
and did the beginning of the film.
It's not a great way to work-
doing it out of context-
because there's always a natural
flow and feel for the sound
as it develops throughout the movie.
But we had no choice
because there were certain scenes...
that hadn't come together yet.
The special effects were not
completed enough in many scenes...
to warrant mixing
the first few reels of the movie.
LUCAS: This briefing room scene
is what we call the "pointer scene."
A pointer scene is where
you sit down and tell the audience...
all the things that have to happen,
or are going to happen
in the rest of the movie
so they can follow the plot.
We have to go to the castle.
This is the way we get to the castle.
These are the dangers
we have to overcome.
Then there's the prize at the end.
And there is in almost every movie
a pointer scene...
where everybody sits down and says,
well, this is what's gonna happen.
In some scenes it's just very blatant.
They have a chalkboard and a pointer.
They draw a diagram and say
this is what we have to do.
All these scenes are pointer scenes.
You can see in A New Hope,
when we did the pointer scene
toward the end about the Death Star,
that was pretty much
the state of the art
in terms
of computer animation at that point.
Now, in this film we pretty much
have the same scene,
but computer
animation has advanced quite a bit.
Both of those were done
through the use of computer animation-
the original Death Star illustration
and this particular new Death Star.
Part of the advancing technology
is it allows you to do more things,
to have a more epic quality to things...
which gets more sophisticated
as you go along,
both because you can master
the technology...
and because you have
a better grasp...
of literally just how to do things.
How to get more people in masks.
There's a whole science
behind people acting in masks.
They can't stay
in the mask very long.
It's hard for them to breathe.
Some people get claustrophobic.
Again, on each one
of these characters...
there's two or three people
with remote controls moving the eyes.
For every one of these people
there's three or four other people...
standing on the sidelines
trying to operate them.
So, if you have three or four
puppet characters...
you have a huge number of people
on the side
trying to make them all work.
In each film, we were able
to add more and more people in...
because we got better at
doing that sort of thing.
The story progresses...
from being a very contained
environment in A New Hope...
to a bigger environment
in The Empire Strikes Back.
And then, obviously,
when we get to Return of the Jedi...
we're able to have
large fleets of ships,
more exotic environments,
more stormtroopers.
We've learned how to
build the scale up,
you know, while still staying
within our financial resources.
Sort of more frequencies
on the transmitters.
Pushing the edge of special effects
in order to tell a more interesting story,
you're always sort of on the edge
of having it not work.
And then the whole film falls apart.
Because it is a facade.
It's an illusion.
Especially a fantasy film of any kind.
You're creating a fantastic illusion
that people know isn't real.
So you have to make it kind of...
super-believable,
even though it's impossible
and can't possibly be real.
We've used about every possible
special effects technique...
you can imagine
over the years in these movies.
Almost everything that is doable...
and has been done
is represented someplace.
Which is one of the reasons everybody
had a lot of fun doing these films...
'cause there was always
a different kind of effect,
always a different challenge.
A lot of classic situations
that had to be dealt with.
It was a chance to do something
that doesn't come up very often.
The scene with the Millennium Falcon
and Lando...
is a way of putting a little bit
of an edge on the film...
that Han Solo doesn't think
he's gonna ever see his ship again.
There's concern
something may happen to him,
something may happen to Lando.
It brings up the possibility that some
of the characters could be in jeopardy.
BURTT: We've had lots of adventures
recording sound over the years.
A lot of the switches and buttons
you hear inside the shuttle craft...
were actually recorded on board
an old World War II submarine...
that was in dry dock,
but we were allowed to go on board.
It was very quiet, but the nice thing
about the submarine was...
it's a confined space
with metal walls and ceiling.
So, when you turn the switches
and click buttons and things...
they have a real natural,
real sound to them 'cause they are real.
We had actually gone on board a sub
to record a lot of material...
for Raiders of the Lost Ark.
And had a bit of a library there,
and we recycled them through
the Star Wars films whenever
we needed that kind of sound.
LUCAS: The emperor's outpost
on the Death Star is a tall spire.
It's reminiscent of-
when you see the first three trilogies-
of the Jedi temple.
In this case, the-
there's one spire on the Death Star...
and the Jedi temple's got five spires.
One of the more exciting parts
about making films is that...
you come up with an idea that
you don't know you can accomplish...
and then, at some point,
it starts to come together.
You see it on the screen the way you
thought it would be, and it works.
It's a big thrill. It's especially exciting
in the world of special effects...
where it's something
that just can't happen...
and then suddenly you see it
on the big screen, and there it is.
With performances
of the actors or the characters,
there's a magic that happens when
you put all the elements together...
and they're saying their lines
and doing what their supposed to do...
in the right environment
and it all comes to life.
It's a very rewarding feeling.
BURTT: A good sound designer
always keeps his ears...
and eyes open in everyday life...
because some of the best sounds
that we've recorded,
the most useful sounds, are just things
you encounter sometimes by accident.
Sometimes you're on a family trip,
or you're out shopping.
I've gone to stores, and I've opened
the cabinet to get a soft drink
out of the refrigerator cabinet...
and I can hear a broken motor
that's in the cabinet.
You-You know, I run out to the car
and get the recorder and come back in
and record that funny motor.
And it becomes the sound
of a speeder or something.
Those kinds of events
happen all the time,
and you have to be alert to them.
Because some of the best sound effects
come from things out of everyday life.
Not the kind of sounds which you
very carefully orchestrate...
in a studio somewhere
where it's all quiet...
and maybe it's acoustically
a little bit of an artificial place,
'cause no place sounds like a studio.
Sounds in the real world are often
a lot more interesting and natural...
because they come with a built-in
environment connected to the sound-
a little bit of echo,
the sense of a place.
Therefore a naturalness.
And part of the trick in all
the sound effects in Star Wars...
is to give the film
a sense of credibility.
The sound can give what is otherwise
fantastic and maybe artificial...
a dimension of credibility.
And therefore using real sounds
as often as possible,
recorded outside
under everyday conditions,
often is the most useful
kind of raw material
to orchestrate into the soundtrack.
LUCAS: The thing about Endor is that...
I wanted an environment...
that was different
from the other environments.
But it needed to be
a jungly kind of place.
A lot of growth and green,
which is the color of life and-
I wanted to give it a different look
than Dagobah,
which in essence
had the same qualities.
It was a swamp. It was, again, a cradle
of life environment-lots of life there.
But I was beginning
to run out of environments,
you know, something that was unique.
The only thing I could come up with
was really giant sequoias...
where the trees would be so big that
it would give it a different look...
than what we'd seen before.
The reason I was able to move on
and do the first three films...
was because I was able to create
digital environments.
By the time I got down here to
Return of the Jedi,
I'd just pretty much shot
everything on Earth. [CHUCKLES]
The speeder bike chase turned into
a very fun experience.
I love speed and racing
and chasing and that sort of stuff.
This was one of those ideas I had
when I was writing the script
that I really wanted to do,
but I had no idea
how we would accomplish this.
Usually, I have a guess of how
I might be able to do it and-
You know, I thought maybe we could
do it with miniatures or something.
We could figure out a way.
I made a leap of faith and left it...
to Dennis Muren to figure it out.
Dennis came up with
a very unique way...
of doing stop-motion animation
in the forest environment,
which had never been done before.
And it really created
these sensational backgrounds.
That was the biggest challenge here.
It was the one time in all these movies
where I came up with an idea...
that I didn't know
that I could pull off.
Now a scene like this with digital
technology would be very easy to do.
But in those days
it was next to impossible.
MUREN: This is one of the funnest
sequences I worked on...
in any of the Star Wars films-
the speeder bike chase.
We shot it in Eureka-
north of Eureka, California...
and just slightly south
of Eureka, California
where these redwood forests were.
The speeder bikes in these are
pretty much most of the time models.
And then we had the actors
for a week or two against bluescreen
for close-ups and medium shots.
And the models are probably
about two-feet wide...
in wider shots
that are motion controlled.
And the backgrounds were shot-
side views were driving along in a car
on a road looking at redwoods.
The front views and back views
were done with a Steadicam.
Garrett Brown, who invented the
Steadicam, walking along in the woods
at about four or five miles an hour...
shooting one frame of film a second,
sort of stop-motion style.
When you put them together,
you end up with this feeling...
that you're going along
at a hundred miles an hour
in any direction.
But it was a really neat sequence.
The sort of jumpy quality that you got
with the Steadicam views,
the front views and back views,
added a real energy to it.
It made it look like it was difficult
to shoot, the jumping up and down on it.
It was something that George
really responded to right away-
something that was unintentional,
but it added a reality to it...
that you wouldn't have gotten if you'd
built it as a model or something
and had a nice smooth camera
going along.
It's sort of an artifact of the hundred
miles an hour that you're traveling...
gave it a real dynamic to it-
a documentary kind of look to it.
See, in all those backgrounds there,
you can see how they're kind of
trembling, and they're never level.
All these cameras jumping around,
just trying to do it.
That's just Garrett trying to do
the best job he can keeping it steady.
But at one frame a second you're never
gonna quite be able to do that.
BURTT: The gear shifts
and the various sounds of the bikes...
changing tones as they went
different speeds-
the principal sound for that
came about in a funny way.
I was in England, in an office,
during the production of the movie
and I was doing some paperwork.
I heard outside, coming from
the street, near the studio...
a very strange sound-
kind of a coughing, but musical sound.
And I went outside,
and I saw some men
that were trying to repair a pothole.
And they had an air hammer
that they were trying to use,
but it had gotten a rock
caught in the rubber hose...
which fed the air to the hammer.
And so as they activated the hammer,
they were actually playing
a funny musical instrument.
I said, "Please, don't fix it. Let me go
get my recorder. I'll be right back."
Obviously they looked at me like I was
pretty strange, but they tolerated it.
I came back a few moments later
with my recorder.
We recorded
that funny air compressor...
and used it for the sounds
of the bikes shifting gears.
George Lucas came by to listen
to the speeder bike chase...
when I thought it had been completed,
and he sat through it-he hadn't
heard any of the sounds before.
He liked it, but he had a comment
that it didn't seem quite real enough.
It didn't have
quite enough presence to it.
His suggestion was
that we put in the sound...
of snapping branches and leaves,
and the kind of noises you'd get...
if those bikes were really
zooming through the forest...
and clipping the edges of foliage
and shrubs and so on.
So we very quickly put together some
sounds of brush and crackling sticks...
and we made some loops of the sound-
that is, continuously playing sounds-
and we went back through
the speeder bike chase...
and we would ramp in those sounds
so there'd be a brief burst...
of just sticks and dirt noise and grit.
LUCAS: We started with the Ewoks...
who were,
in the original screenplay, Wookiees...
that I couldn't use
because I'd established...
that Wookiees were a technologically
advanced group of creatures.
I needed to come up
with a primitive creature...
that was still using sticks and stones
and spears for weapons...
and lived in a primitive society...
that would be forced to take on
the highly technological Empire.
So, ultimately, I decided to keep
the characters sort of fuzzy and hairy.
But instead of having long hair,
I gave them short hair.
Instead of making them tall,
I made them short.
So we had a lot of little people
that we put in costumes.
Again, technology is limited
in what we can do
to create these kind of creatures
and make them real.
Mostly it depends on the personality
of the actor inside the suit.
And I was fortunate
to find this one Ewok,
this little boy, Warwick Davis,
who was so expressive in his suit
and had such personality-
the way he walked
and the way he carried himself,
the way he was able to act-
he really was a hundred percent
into the character.
Again, the challenge of creating
a likable character...
out of a kid in a bear suit
that actually has a personality
as a character-
isn't just somebody who's there-
is very difficult.
You're always pushed to
how far can you go...
in having strange creatures,
exotic creatures...
who are actual characters
in the movie...
using this kind of,
you know, "real" technology-
a real puppet
or a real person in a suit.
Which was about all we had
in those days. It was very limiting.
FISHER: After a while,
it was very difficult for me
to do action sequences...
where I punched people
and hit people.
It's not really my thing.
It's stressful.
You pretend that you're shooting
at people and shooting guns...
and you're upset,
and you're crazed all morning long.
And so I'm revving up this thing
that is not innate in me necessarily.
And I can be
a pretty intense... broad.
But, you know, after a certain
amount of time, I was... done.
And you can't be done.
You have to keep going.
LUCAS: Warwick was so good in this
that I had been thinking about doing...
another kind of more traditional
fantasy that involved little people
and got him to star in that.
He's done a lot of roles since.
But that film was Willow,
directed by Ron Howard.
Now, as we get into
the last reels here of the film...
we're into the pulling
the plot together,
which ultimately is the trap
that the rebels are falling into.
The trap that Luke is falling into.
The trap that the emperor
has been planning to do away
with all his enemies.
So now this takes all of the dominoes
that have been set up...
in A New Hope
and Empire Strikes Back
and the first part of this film...
and starts to tip them over,
which in this particular case...
is reasonably complicated
'cause we have
three different stories going on-
One is in outer space with Lando
and the spaceships trying
to get into the Death Star.
One is on the planet
with Han Solo and Princess Leia...
trying to destroy the force field
that protects the Death Star.
And then you have Luke Skywalker
on the Death Star...
confronting his father and
the evil head of the Galactic Empire.
I do like to tell
a lot of different stories
and cut back and forth.
I'm not a big linear storyteller.
American Graffiti, there were four
stories being told simultaneously.
They were all going very fast.
I like simultaneity
and jumping back and forth.
That's what I'm most comfortable with,
for whatever reason.
Well, my first film, THX,
wasn't like that.
It was completely linear-
didn't cut back and forth with anything.
But after that I changed my mind.
[CHUCKLES]
BURTT: The hardest thing to create
in these films for me...
is always the voices.
Sound effects is one issue.
But voices are listened to...
with a very critical ear
by the audience.
We're all experts at
identifying voices
and understanding
where they come from...
and read into all
the nuances of voice quality,
intonation and performance.
The biggest voice task in Jedi
was the development...
of the Ewok languages
and the Ewok character voices.
The first step was to create a language.
Now, I don't create a language really
by sitting down...
and trying to reason it out
as to what the cultural context is...
and how I'm gonna conjugate verbs
or any of that.
Generally speaking, we've worked...
by first listening
to actual voice recordings...
from around the world
of different languages...
until we find a language
which sounds exotic, not familiar,
and has something of
the character of the types of aliens
we're trying to create.
Even though
we don't speak that language,
we'll listen to recordings of it...
and we'll begin to extract sounds
from that language...
and eventually build up
kind of a double-talk set of sounds...
in which we're mimicking
this exotic language.
The Ewok language
is really derivative of Kalmyk,
which is a language
that comes out of Asia...
in areas of central China.
I saw a documentary on television...
that interviewed some people
in this region of China-
some nomadic tribesmen-
"and I thought," Wow.
This language is very interesting.
"It has something
we haven't heard before.
It seems like it would be
something good for the Ewoks."
We began to look around to see
if we could find anyone
that spoke this language.
Of course, there wasn't offhand
anybody immediately available...
since it came from
a remote part of the world.
But we finally, through some research,
came into contact with some refugees...
who had come from that part of China.
And in particular, an elderly woman-
she was probably in her 80s-
was brought to us.
She didn't speak any English.
She had recently immigrated
from primitive regions of China.
She had lived in a tribe...
as some kind of a quasi-nomadic
existence all her life.
She probably didn't really understand
what we were trying to do
in recording her voice for a movie.
But we approach these things...
by usually bringing the person
into the studio...
and I sit down with them.
You get her to tell stories.
This is usually how I do it.
A person who's not an actor...
you just don't put a microphone
in front of them and say, "Okay, talk."
You usually wanna put them at ease
and give them something to do.
What I found with her and what
I've done with other native people...
was to sit down with them
and have them tell me folk tales...
and to pretend
they were telling me stories,
bedtime stories, as if I was a child.
They can tell me a story
in which they may do
the voices of different characters...
and they can inject a sense of drama
into what they're saying.
She wanted a bottle of vodka
and, uh, we provided that for her.
And she got very lucid and gave us
some wonderful sounds.
We referred to this woman
as "Grandma Vodka"...
because we couldn't pronounce
her real name.
And a session in the studio with her...
gave us not only the inspiration
but gave us the basis...
for a lot of the Ewok voices.
We were able to take recordings
that she gave us...
of her laughing,
of her telling stories,
of her doing
little character voices high and low...
and out of that
came a range of sounds,
both male and female voices,
which provided the basis
for the Ewok language.
Once we got comfortable
with orchestrating those sounds...
and picking out the things we liked,
then we brought
in our own staff of actors-
usually people on our own crew.
Also, people in the Bay Area
that we knew...
who had interesting quality
to their voices.
They either had a high-pitched voice
or they had a very raspy kind of voice.
And we brought them in,
played these recordings of Kalmyk...
and had them imitate it.
And we wrote out phonetically
things for people to say.
We assigned particular voices
we liked to certain Ewok characters...
like Wicket
or the chief of the village...
or the witch doctor of the village.
And then the crowd sounds
of the Ewoks were our crew members...
imitating what they had heard
in these exotic languages.
And it was just all put together...
in kind of a collage that unto itself,
I guess, ended up having
a consistent sound to it.
One of the favourite recordings we got
from this elderly Chinese woman...
was a little song that she sang
which you'll hear several times
in the Ewok village...
when they get excited
or they make a decision...
as they pass the firewood.
It's probably based on some
Chinese folk song. I really don't know.
LUCAS: There was a big challenge
with these Ewoks...
to make them realistic and believable.
It was very hard to get much movement
in the face or much individuality...
so you could recognise them
as different characters...
and believe that
they were threatening at all.
They're designed to be kind of
cute and fuzzy little teddy bears.
I mean, they are the ones
that save the day in the end.
And so they had to have
this dual capacity-
one, to be kind of
cute and inconsequential...
and then at the same time at the end
be tough enough to conduct a war...
that you'd believe
that they could actually do it.
I knew there would be a lot of,
especially older kids...
that would just have
a hard time buying into this idea.
But we decided to do it anyway.
Because we had so many
Ewoks in this film,
we couldn't really do
remote control eyes and eyelids...
because we just didn't have enough
remote control mechanisms.
And we couldn't
make their mouths move.
So the actors had to make the mouths
move just by moving their jaw.
And actually Warwick Davis
got very good at using his tongue...
and sticking his tongue out a lot
and sort of moving it around.
It really gave the sense
that the lips were moving
and something was going on there.
All it really was
was him sticking his tongue out.
But I think there's
an impression that the mouths move,
even though they actually don't.
Some of the actors got pretty good
at moving their jaw.
But it was very hard to do,
and it was very tiresome.
If we were doing it today,
we'd have a lot more detail
in the Ewoks.
I think we'd probably do it digitally.
We'd have a couple of suits
for the lead characters probably.
Most of the other ones
would be done digitally.
We're coping with that now
with Wookiees...
'cause there's a lot of Wookiees
in the next movie.
It's the same problem we had here.
You know, where do you get
enough people that tall?
In this case, it was how do you
get enough people that small?
If you're gonna have a scene
with several hundred...
you're sort of-it's very difficult to do.
BURTT: The scene where 3PO
tells the story to the Ewoks...
of their adventures
and how they got to the Ewok forest...
is one of my favourite
sound effects moments.
Tony Daniels
was absolutely brilliant here...
in that he did a sign language
and an audio recreation...
of events in the Star Wars movies-
the walkers, the spaceships,
the lightsabers.
Together, Tony and I worked out
the Ewok language
that he would speak...
based on what we were
developing for the Ewoks.
Tony made up a lot of the words himself
and was very clever
about the whole thing.
And then we integrated
into his speech the sound effects-
sound effects that were from
our library of Star Wars sounds.
The idea was that 3PO was actually
playing back these sounds...
over his built-in mouth speaker...
in order to articulate the story
to the Ewoks.
It's a fun capsulization of
the signature Star Wars sounds-
the lightsaber, the Millennium Falcon,
the walkers, and so on.
We went out into the woods-
into the Redwoods here in
Northern California where it was quiet-
and we did a lot of off screen yells and
laughs and cries as if we were Ewoks.
We can always take our voices
and pitch them up a little bit...
so that we sound smaller and cuter.
And once you get
some recordings like that,
which are actually recorded
out in the real woods,
the forest has
a wonderful acoustic quality to it.
It's one of those places
where you can really sense depth...
because of the way
echoes and sounds travel in a forest.
And once again, if you take some of
those real-sounding recordings...
and mix them in with those done in
the studio, it has a more natural sound.
LUCAS: This again was one of those...
difficult scenes...
because there's a lot of exposition.
A lot of things that need to be
tied up and confronted and resolved...
which sends the film
in a particular direction...
that is more about explaining things
than it is about drama.
But there are times when the material
will dictate what you have to do...
in order to make the film work.
So if you're into the movies and
you're into what the problems are...
and who's who and what's what,
then it becomes a fascinating scene.
If you're looking to follow the plot
and just get on with the movie,
then it's one of those
hard-to-get-through scenes.
It's the kind of thing you're
always trying to balance in a movie,
which is how much exposition
do you give out and-
Unfortunately, I gave out very
little exposition in the first movie.
So I saved it all up
pretty much till the third movie.
And at this point, you kind of had
to tie all the ends together...
and have the people react
to those things being tied up.
The discussion here
is one of those scenes
you wanna have to never write.
[LAUGHS]
It's one thing for Darth Vader
to tell Luke that he's his father...
and it's another thing
to have Luke tell Leia
that he has a sister
and that Darth Vader is his father.
That really gets hard to swallow.
It's a real challenge
to pull it off and make it come out...
with dialogue that is at least sincere
and believable with honest reactions.
You got these characters
that have been around for a long time.
One's telling,
"By the way, you're my sister.
Darth Vader's my father,
and he's also your father."
Most stories, it takes the whole movie
to explain that part.
They're very carefully constructed
and put together.
Here, I have to dump it out
in one little scene.
The voice is strong in my family.
My father has it.
BURTT: I remember this scene
of Luke and Leia...
on the Ewok balcony
with great anxiety,
because I was on the set this day...
and the boom operator
offered me the opportunity...
to be the boom operator on one scene,
'cause I always wanted that experience.
So I said, "Sure, I'll do it."
So this meant that I had
a long fish pole, as it's called,
about eight to 10 feet long,
and on the end of it's a microphone.
And we were up on the stage.
We were probably
20 feet off the ground...
on a scaffolding
adjacent to this walkway...
where Luke and Leia
are having their conversation.
My job was to hold this pole
out from the scaffolding...
and out over their heads
while they had this scene of dialogue.
Well, there was no rehearsal
before they shot the scene...
so I found that I wasn't in
a real comfortable position.
And when they called "Roll it,"
this was something like...
a two- or three-minute-long scene
of the two of them talking...
in absolute quietness on the set.
And I was having trouble
holding onto the mic.
It was beginning to come out
of my hands and dip into the scene,
and I was so afraid
I was gonna drop the fish pole...
and the mic would
hit Carrie Fisher in the forehead,
therefore ruining the scene
and ending my career forever in sound.
FISHER: He wears the same outfit
for three flicks...
and I was complaining that...
I wear, like, six outfits...
and my mother, Natalie Portman,
she wears three million.
She walks through a doorway,
and there's another outfit.
It's like the Liberace of sci-fi
changing of clothes.
In the first film,
I wore two outfits-
one for the whole movie
and one for the medal-giving.
And now there's, like,
a couple of outfits.
But Harrison-
just one outfit, right?
So I should not complain.
"Oh, my darling, hold me."
It was better when we were fighting.
LUCAS: In the Special Edition,
there was very little done to this movie.
Most of the work was actually done
in A New Hope...
because that was the one
that was made under the most stress,
where we fell short of what
I was really trying to get accomplished.
By the time we got down to
this movie, there was very little...
that I didn't get accomplished
that I wanted to get accomplished.
A lot of that has to do with the fact
that this is a much more personal story.
I wasn't pushing
the envelope technologically
to try to tell a story
that I couldn't tell.
Because the real focus of this
is really the battle...
between Luke and his father.
It's the emotional core of the picture.
BURTT: I went into Jedi
knowing how much...
dialogue replacement had gone on
in the previous two Star Wars films.
It was frustrating because
going through the ADR process
after the fact...
is hard on everybody-it's hard
on the actors, hard on the director.
It's difficult to get
a natural sound to the voices...
when they're done a year later
on a stage out of context.
And I wanted to try...
to make a much better effort
to get a good, usable production sound.
But in most Star Wars films,
there's a lot of noises on the set.
I kind of gave up getting
perfect production tracks...
on the Star Wars films because...
there were always so many
interfering noises.
If you had stormtroopers in the scene,
their plastic costumes
made a lot of racket...
and interfered with getting
intelligible dialogue.
Obviously, you have characters
like Vader or Chewbacca...
in which you've got actors inside
the suits trying to do the dialogue...
and the best you can get
out of them is a guide track
because their voices are very muffled.
And quite often, Vader, of course-
The actor in the suit for Vader is not
the voice that will be there in the final.
It's only a voice to use
as a guide track on the set itself.
So for lots of reasons,
the dialogue is pretty much done over...
once you get back into
the editorial phase of the movie.
Probably only about 15%
of the original dialogue...
recorded on the set
ends up in the final movie.
LUCAS: This scene, where Luke
deliberately gets himself captured...
and confronts Vader,
sort of defines the rest of the movie...
in terms of the fact that it's not a chase,
or one trying to escape from the other,
but it's an emotional confrontation
between the two of 'em.
Luke isn't gonna run away from him.
He isn't gonna fight him.
It's a whole different twist on where
you might expect the movie might go.
It becomes a direct challenge
that Luke has with his father to say...
"I dare you.
I'm not gonna run away from this."
Which makes it very different
than keeping them as villains...
or a villain-hero kind of situation.
It's "We're gonna sit down
and talk about this."
Again, on a lot of levels, there's some
nice twists in their relationship...
in how they confront each other,
but it's not like in Empire Strikes Back...
where it was actually a physical
confrontation and cutting arms off
and things like that.
This is a more emotional,
talking kind of confrontation.
This film was written
during the Vietnam War...
where a small group
of ill-equipped people...
were able to overcome a mighty power.
It's not a new idea. Attila the Hun
was able to overrun the Roman Empire.
The American colonies
were able to overrun the British.
That's always the same story.
The Roman Empire had
huge mechanical advantage...
and training advantage
over the Huns,
but the Huns were still able
to overwhelm them...
with sort of enthusiasm
and their humanism
and their belief
in what they were doing.
And that was the main theme for
the overall downfall of the Empire,
that it was basically
overcome by humanity...
in the form of cute little teddy bears.
MUREN: Here's the burst to light speed.
The original version
for the first Star Wars-
I think Richard Edlund did that.
It's streak photography-
stuff he'd used a lot
when he was working at Bob Abel's.
The camera moves from one position
to another during one frame of film.
Then it does a slightly different camera
move through the next frame of film...
but covers some of the same area
it did the first time.
You end up with something looking
like it's stretching and then popping off.
A lot of television commercials Abel's
guys did in the late '70s and '80s...
have got that same
streak photography stuff.
It became quite popular.
You can sort of go back even to 2001,
which is some of the first time
that had actually been done
in the slit-scan stuff...
that Trumbull brought to that show.
So here it is as the jump to hyperspeed
in Star Wars. Same idea.
LUCAS: The interesting part
of making movies is that...
it's very hard to understand
the amount of detail...
that you have to overcome
in terms of making it look easy.
You know, the amount of study
and training and craft...
on everybody's part
all the way down the line.
You know, and if somebody doesn't do
it right-their little piece right,
then it instantly shows up on the screen
and becomes a distraction.
And the amount of just plain hard work
it takes to get to a particular point...
to get the lines out right, to make sure
the lines are right in the first place.
In this particular scene,
the Ewoks jumping on the speeders-
the problem of getting
the Ewok up on the speeder-
because the Ewok is very short,
and the speeder was sitting...
about three feet off the ground.
It was taller than the Ewok.
How to get him up there...
just physically, and make it believable
takes a lot of scratching of heads.
We actually tossed him up there.
[CHUCKLES] A couple guys threw him.
MUREN: So here's another
speeder bike chase going on...
using a lot of the same elements
we'd used for
the major sequence earlier.
Same approaches.
These are model speeders...
when you see 'em full frame
that are moved along.
And mainly, the camera's doing
most of the motions.
If you look at
some of these backgrounds
where you're going straight ahead...
or looking straight back,
you might see a little white line...
over on one side of the frame,
and what that is
is a string
that we had along the walkway.
We're trying to keep the camera
at the correct height...
and that string represents
a height of about six feet.
As the terrain changed, Garrett Brown,
the Steadicam operator...
kept trying to keep the camera
at that height.
So it was always, like,
six feet above the ground
even though
the ground was changing height.
And sometimes it shows.
You see that little string going by.
But it sort of adds
to the chaos of the shots.
LUCAS: There's a lot of work that goes
into the design of these films...
that has to do with
the actual design of the frame.
Color plays an extremely
important part in all these films.
You know, red signifying evil-
the red blood, the red devil.
Red as an accent color
for the bad guys.
The bad guys mostly exist
in a black-and-white world.
The good guys live
in an organic world...
which is either browns-
light browns, tans-
or greens, you know,
with the blue sky and stuff.
But mostly it's the good guys
are green and brown...
the bad guys are black-and-white,
which has to do as much
with anything-
It really has to do with that feeling-
a philosophical feeling...
of a world of absolutes.
A mechanical world where things
are rigid and absolute.
They're black-and-white,
as opposed to the organic world
where it's more natural.
And, you know,
right, wrong, black, white.
These kind of things don't exist...
at least symbolically,
in that world.
Things are more natural.
Part of this stuff, in terms of-like this
where the window looks like a web,
which it does in all
of the Sith and imperial stuff-
You'll see it in Darth Vader's-
In Episode IV, the TIE fighters
have that same motif.
It's a motif we carry through
for the bad guy.
It's designed really
just to give you that feeling.
It's a symbolic motif
that goes through that allows-
Say, "These are bad guys. These are
the people you have to be afraid of."
And he is the spider
luring the flies into his web.
'Cause he's the plotter.
He's the devious one.
MUREN: The nice thing about this
is that we had
so many different departments
that were all so good at what they did.
And, really, when you're looking
at the Star Wars films...
you're looking at the work
of a good dozen groups of people...
that are real experts
at what they're doing...
and focusing on their skill set
and contributing...
whether it's building the models
or doing the laser blasts...
or the pyro blasts
or the photography on it...
or the optical compositing that's
putting all the scenes together...
or the storyboards or whatever.
They're all really a great group
of people that had worked together-
By this time, we had been
working together for six or eight years
or so and really had it down.
I think Jedi shows as
the most polished of all the shows...
just because we really
had figured out how to do it.
And all the energy on this show
could go into the shot design-
coming up with designs
that were different and new and fresh.
BURTT: I had the opportunity to play
a very minor part in the film...
as an imperial officer
in the Endor power station...
who jumps out from behind a wall
at the power station...
and holds a gun on Han Solo
and then get hit with kind of
what was like a toolbox...
falling into a generator room below.
My big line was "Freeze!"
Freeze!
The voice of
Billy Dee Williams's co-pilot...
was recorded by a young man...
who was a foreign student
from Kenya who spoke Haya,
which was one of the native languages
of that country.
He came in, and we explained
to him what we wanted.
I wrote out some lines
of dialogue in English...
that would fit
the context of the story...
and he translated them
into his native tongue.
And we did a recording session
with him...
and his voice was dubbed in
for the co-pilot.
Of course, in most parts of the world,
nobody could understand
that language.
But when this film
played in Kenya...
people suddenly understood their
own language in the Star Wars movie...
and got so excited about it.
Fortunately, he was saying
the appropriate lines of dialogue...
that fit into the story,
so it had all the more meaning...
to the people who could understand it.
MUREN: As the shows went on,
we got better...
at shooting bluescreen faster
so we could set the models up.
But the techniques
were all pretty much the same
all the way through the shows.
What we got better
at was programming.
We could program models faster,
so we had these shots...
where there's hundreds of ships
going by.
Like this sort of sequence here,
which is a big Ken Ralston sequence.
There's one shot where he's got-
I think he said...
120 separate
motion-controlled spaceships in it.
It was so big what George wanted.
It came from our skill getting better
and faster at being able to do the work.
There wasn't really a big breakthrough
in the technology during these shows...
that I could really see.
LUCAS: In the original screenplay,
this was the attack.
There was a Wookiee planet.
The end with the Death Star
and the Wookiee attack...
was all together
at the end of the movie.
But then when I went
and did only the first movie...
I kind of took the Death Star battle out
and put it into the first movie.
So that's why ultimately I had
to create a second Death Star.
But that was all originally-
There was only one Death Star...
and it all culminated
in this one giant battle...
with the Wookiees on the planet
battling the Death Star...
and this confrontation with Luke...
and Vader and the emperor.
MUREN: The walking machines
that are in this sequence
are what we call the "chicken walker"...
that was in one scene
of Empire Strikes Back.
It was just an idea I think
that Joe Johnston just came up with.
And we just made a model
and stuck it in one of the scenes...
and it got a lot of comment
'cause it was so cute-looking.
We added that background walker
walking through...
just to give a sense
of some action going on...
so it wasn't just sort of static-
like they're patrol walkers.
It kept the sequence more interesting.
This full-size walker was out there.
I wonder where that walker is today.
This location was, I believe,
one that was about
to be cut down anyway for logging.
So it was all right to go in
and sort of blow these trees up.
I thought it was too bad
that had to happen,
but here it is on film, and at least
that process entertained people...
before it actually got-
just everything cut down.
BURTT: Added to the library
of high-tech lasers and walkers...
we also, of course, had the weapons
that the Ewoks were using-
mostly bows and arrows.
I was always greatly
inspired by the movie
The Adventures of Robin Hood,
the 1938 version,
which had a wonderful
and very unique sound to the arrows.
They used a very particular
kind of homemade arrow.
And we found someone
who understood
how those arrows were made.
And when we made arrows
on that pattern...
they gave a really nice zinging sound.
We recorded them and used them
for the sounds of the Ewok archers.
LUCAS: This is the part of the movie
was a real struggle
in terms of believability.
The style of Star Wars
is a little bit light-hearted
and doesn't take itself too seriously.
But at the same time,
it has to be believable and realistic...
that these funny little bears
with bows and arrows...
could actually confront stormtroopers.
It's a big challenge.
You set yourself up
for particular characters
and when it comes time to-
the confrontation...
you hope you've given 'em
enough stuff to make it work.
In this particular case,
I think I established...
part of the credibility of the Ewoks
by simply not having them win.
I mean, occasionally, they-
Toward the end they start to win,
but they lose so much
in the beginning of this battle.
What you think is gonna happen
actually does happen,
which is they're absolutely no match.
It makes it more believable
that what happens later on is
they do the same kind of thing.
They start to get
a little bit more successful at it.
But never do they actually
overcome them.
It's really the battle in the sky.
That is where the real battles go down.
This is really just the battle...
to get in to blow up
the protective shield generator...
which means that all
the Ewoks really have to do...
is distract the troops,
which is believable.
They could actually pull them away
and engage them enough...
to keep them occupied while
the generator is blown up.
MUREN: These were different ideas
about how you knock
these machines over.
And we had some cute
little things here where...
we sort of give the machines
a little sense of personality-
the walking machines.
Even though they're going along and
blasting things, they're not invincible.
Sometimes the simplest little things
can destroy technology,
which is sort of a theme
in George's movies.
Another big Ken Ralston
battle scene here.
This is what Ken did for
most of the show-
was doing these massive,
massive battle scenes...
and so many of them
way beyond anything we'd done before.
And a lot more spatial sense, where
things would be way in the distance
and come up way close to the camera.
I think for some of these shots
we also made even smaller models
and lengthened our track...
so the model could be a lot smaller
at the beginning of a shot...
or at the end of a shot
than it had been before.
LUCAS: This was a chance for us
to make a more complex dogfight...
and battle in space
than we did in A New Hope...
with more ships
and more complicated moves.
This was taking the process
of these kinds of space battles...
to, like, the furthest degree I think
anybody's ever been able to take them-
I mean, using this kind of technology,
which is analogue technology.
The way these are done is
they're sort of run through a printer
over and over and over again.
The more ships,
the more times you have to run through.
Some of the shots in
this sequence took 24 hours
just to run through the printer.
So then you'd look at it,
and if there was anything wrong...
one mistake made on one frame,
you had to go back and redo it again.
Every time you did it,
there was a chance...
that somewhere along the line
you'd make a mistake...
because you were trying to make sure
that all of the sequences...
were put in the printer exactly
the same way
and the same frame
had to line up with the same frame.
You had to do this for all the mattes
and all of the shots...
and all of the objects
that are in the frame.
And it got to be very, very difficult.
Looking at dailies on some of the shots
in that sequence of the spaceships
got to be very traumatic...
because there was so much
time and money invested.
And you just had no idea whether
it was gonna turn out or not.
MUREN: So the battle is picking up.
There's more explosions,
a lot of which were actually
done on the location.
Trees knocked over on location.
Powder charges going off on location.
We would put our walkers into 'em
and make it look like they had caused
a lot the damage in the first place.
BURTT: The final battle,
which involved so many elements-
It was really a collection
of lots of different sound threads...
that had been running
through the previous Star Wars films.
When we got to
the final battle in the Ewok forest,
these elements all came together.
We had all these sets of lasers
we had developed
over the course of two films
prior to this-
the walker lasers,
all the stormtrooper lasers and so on.
Of course, we had quite
a big library of explosions now.
And we were adding to it
the Ewok voices, the cries, the yells-
things we recorded out in the woods
and manufactured their battle cries.
The chicken walkers
were really an extract
from what had been developed...
from the four-legged walkers
in The Empire Strikes Back.
It's just a higher-pitched
and faster walking rhythm.
MUREN: The animation effects
that are in these shows...
whether the laser's firing
or the beams going out...
and meeting and shooting into
a superpowered beam or something are
are really important
to the Star Wars movies.
That was a whole department in itself...
that did the laser effects
and the explosion effects.
It's quite a creative group, too,
to be able to do that...
and have 'em be sort of interesting
and look like the beams come
from way of fin the distance...
and travel right by the camera
or vice versa.
LUCAS: Most of this sequence with Luke
really has to do
with making him angry...
and trying to tempt him
to become angry...
and Luke fighting that temptation.
Which, obviously, eventually he does
and eventually again he doesn't.
But that's-The real tension
of this whole scene is,
will he become angry enough
to try to attack the emperor?
What the emperor wants basically
is for him to kill his father
so he can take his place.
Which is the same thing his father
is trying to get him to do,
which is kill the emperor
so Vader can take the emperor's place.
I am defenseless.
Take your weapon and strike me down
with all of your hatred...
and your journey
towards the dark side...
will be complete!
BURTT: I find myself
spending months, if not years...
making trial and error movies...
to evaluate concepts of things.
You know, I'll work for months
and months and months
putting together a chase scene.
It's, you know, 20 minutes long,
and it will have...
10 different possible
variations of it conceptually.
And out of that, "A," it may
never be in the final movie,
even though it has voices
and sound effects
and sound design and music.
And it-You know,
it's an entertainment piece unto itself.
And they're getting
more and more elaborate.
LUCAS: The one advantage I have
is to be able to
sort of follow my own muse...
even if it seems contrary to what
might be best for selling the movie.
[CHUCKLES] I've become
more interested
in the story than anything else.
In this case, the story really is
of a very primitive society,
a-a-apparently, a weak society...
you know, who's able to overcome
a very technological society.
MUREN: So how do you knock over
one of these walking machines?
One way to do it is to sort of like
give it a great big headache.
So they came up with this cute idea
where it gets hit in both sides
and just-crushes it and that's it.
That's done with an oversized model
but pretty much done the way it looked
right there through the camera.
This is a big stop-motion shot
that had to match
with the background
miniature of the logs hitting.
And then we cut in to an oversized
miniature for the actual explosion.
We're mixing the two of them there.
We wanted to get a nice performance...
of the walker trying to keep from falling
over, and then when it hit the ground...
we went to one two or three times
larger for the explosion part of it.
LUCAS: The scene where he says
"I love you" and she says "I know"...
is an echo off the scene
in Empire Strikes Back
where it's just reversed,
which really, in a way, is closing
the circle on their relationship.
It's taken that long
for one to say "I love you"
and the next one to say "I love you."
But now they're doing it,
which ultimately is the culmination...
of their attempts
to connect with each other.
[CHUCKLES] A very slow
and drawn-out process.
The emperor wants Luke to kill Vader
so that he will have a new young Jedi.
Let's face it,
Darth Vader's half mechanical.
He's not nearly
as good as he could be.
He's not nearly as good as
he was hoping Anakin would become...
because he ends up
in this confrontation
which puts him in that suit.
He's hoping to get
a new, better young apprentice in Luke.
And if he kills his father,
then he would
take his place as his apprentice,
which, actually, is something
that happens in the next film.
That's how Anakin
becomes the emperor's apprentice.
There's a lot of stuff that's
repeated through these movies.
I mean,
between this trilogy of IV, V and VI
and the first trilogy of I, II and III.
One is of the father
and the other is of the son.
But there's a lot of scenes
that are similar...
where fathers and sons
confront the same issues
that's almost the same scene.
Thematically,
there's a lot of things like music.
There's certain themes
that keep repeating themselves,
certain situations
that keep repeating themselves.
The only thing that's different
is the performance of the character...
and how does he react to that.
The key issue in these movies
is for a Jedi
not to use anger when he's fighting.
So the final confrontation here
is primarily about
trying to
make Luke become angry...
so that when he fights his father,
he's fighting in anger.
Therefore, begins to use
the dark side of the Force...
and then, therefore, sort of succumbs
to the dark side of the Force.
In The Empire Strikes Back,
we had them confront each other...
and fight together.
But in this one, Luke has become
more mature so that now he knows...
that he shouldn't be fighting him.
That is the path to the dark side.
It's basically a confrontation
between two people
where one of them doesn't want to fight.
And the other one keeps trying
to push him into it.
Then in the end, when he
gives up finally, they really fight.
What's happening there, ultimately,
is that Luke is turning to the dark side.
All is going to be lost.
There is another motif going:
Things aren't what
you would think them to be.
And I like constantly twisting.
You think he's
a harmless little character.
But he's not.
He's a really powerful character.
You think he's a giant,
powerful character. He's not.
He's a nice, loving character.
We're constantly switching
the perception of what everybody is,
which is one of the fun things
about doing a fantasy film.
You play with reality a lot.
This is one of those... areas where...
sometimes I ask myself,
design-wise, what I'm doing.
Because I have characters
like Chewbacca and R2...
in a wide-screen movie, which
is horizontal, and they're vertical.
Here's another one of those examples
in this scene
where I've got a character...
who's completely black in a black suit
in a black cape in a black environment.
[CHUCKLES] In space. In black space.
So it's very hard to make that
actually register.
Just on a plain old technical level,
how do you light something like this?
Normally in a movie,
you wouldn't try that.
In this particular enterprise,
I even got the hero dressed in black.
It's all basically shades of black.
BURTT: The final confrontation
between Vader and Luke...
is one of the first times
that we did a lightsaber fight...
with musical underscore.
We had discovered
in the first Star Wars movie
that the lightsabers themselves
were somewhat musical
by their very nature of the sound.
So we tended to have lightsaber fights
be with sound effects only.
But obviously when it came to this...
super-critical moment
of Luke meeting Vader-
the climax of the movie-
the music was, obviously,
more important in delivering...
the emotional satisfaction to
this moment than the sound effects.
And so John Williams did a terrific cue,
which is always
remembered by people.
It's interesting because that music cue
was not on the original album release...
when the Jedi score came out
at the time this film was first released.
I don't know how many people
asked me over the years,
"When is that piece of music
gonna be released?"
How can I get a copy
of that piece of music?
"That was my favourite moment."
But this final confrontation,
the moment when the choir comes in,
is remembered by many
as a favourite moment in this film.
LUCAS: Normally when you got
several stories going...
what you do is you take 'em
down to the lowest point...
where everything is going wrong
and everybody's in trouble.
And then you bring everybody back...
all at the same time.
They all go down at the same time,
they all come back at the same time.
In this particular case, with this point
where he blows up
the shield generator,
is for Luke the beginning
of the lowest part...
where he just keeps
going down and down and down.
And for the other characters-
for Han and Lando and everybody-
it's where they start
coming back up again.
So they're starting
to achieve their goals,
and Luke is actually losing his goal.
Which, in terms of the storytelling,
lends credibility...
to the fact that maybe Luke is gonna-
maybe they'll blow up the Death Star,
maybe with the emperor in it,
but Luke probably won't survive.
It adds more tension and credibility
to what is going on...
when you've got one of your stories
going out of sync with the other two.
One is fading while the other two
are doing the normal climax
to the end of the movie.
MUREN: Now these electrical bolts
that are going on here...
is a good example
of our animation department.
We had some really good
animators that could do lasers,
they could do electrical bolts,
they could do any sort of rays like that.
And they were hand animated-
you know, drawn on paper as dark lines
and then photographed...
and then comped in as the inverse
of that, as the reverse...
with some nice softening effects
done in the compositing
and when they're added to it.
But you can see there's a whole-
There's a style to it.
There's a whole life of its own...
that the animator would bring to it.
He would try to understand
the point of the shot-is it painful,
is it not painful, or whatever-
and then animate accordingly.
And it's a matter of also
keeping things in scale.
If these bolts are supposed to be,
say, two inches wide by 15 feet long,
when you have a close-up of Luke
it has to be a certain size.
When you're doing a wide shot
and they're smaller in the frame,
they have to be
a lot smaller in the frame
in proportion
to what they really would be.
And that's something a lot of people
doing this work don't understand.
They just make it
sort of the same size...
and can't quite imagine what it would
really be like if it was in the shot.
And our guys were certainly
really good at doing that.
BURTT: We were mixing the scene
where Vader
throws the emperor into the pit...
and we had a temporary version
of the opticals in it.
While we were putting the sounds in-
we were showing it to George-
I suggested, "Why don't we see
the outline of a skull on his face?"
There's just something
that seems to ask for it.
And although the opticals
were already well under way...
he left moments later,
walked next door to ILM...
and came back to the mix saying,
"It's taken care of. We'll see it."
LUCAS: I'll be very curious to see
all six of these films in order...
to see how this very end works
with killing of the emperor...
and the redemption of Darth Vader,
because that becomes
more of the issue
because of the first three films...
than it does in just seeing
these three films by themselves.
In the beginning,
with these three films...
it appeared that the story
was about Luke.
But if you see all six films,
then you realise the story
is really about Darth Vader.
MUREN: And here we go.
This is a different scale Death Star
than from the first show.
A smaller scale so we could go
much farther distances over it.
A lot more detail on it. And getting
ready to go into the tunnels.
And here we are in the tunnels.
And this is one of
Richard Edlund's sequences.
Racing through these tunnels
was quite a complicated thing-
to get the camera in there
and disassemble the set
as we're moving through it.
The camera's shooting
very slowly but continuously,
so as you'd be going through it...
you'd have to be pulling pieces out
of the way that were not on camera...
that were just-right before
the camera was gonna hit it.
The ships, again, are shot all separate.
The explosions are added later on.
You can see the complexity
of the models in that sequence-
how a lot of them are self-illuminated
and other ones are not.
LUCAS: We're constantly moving ships...
closer to ships in outer space
to get some movement out of it.
It's one of the tricks that
we've always been using.
'Cause a ship in space itself,
there's not much dynamic...
because the stars are so far away
and they don't move very fast
unless you're completely parallel.
But whenever you're outside
of a ship or something...
there's hardly any real movement at all.
So in order to create movement
we always put everything
close to something...
so there's always something moving.
We're constantly playing
with space and scale of things...
in characters, in environments,
in everything.
MUREN: This is quite a nice scene here.
The ship finally
sort of meeting its end.
Trying to give it a lot of scale-
little flames-nice, big flames...
with little-very, very tiny on it
not like overtaking it.
Just filling up the whole thing.
Then eventually it does-
The whole thing does blow up.
BURTT: When I originally
developed the breathing sound
for Darth Vader in New Hope...
I had a range of different sounds
going from a very raspy, almost
asthmatic sound of Vader breathing...
up into a more mechanical,
cold-sounding breathing.
And we had opted
in the first Star Wars film...
to go with the colder,
more mechanical breathing.
But when it came to the scene
where he is injured and dying...
and Luke is about ready
to remove his helmet,
we went back to some of
the recordings I had made...
of the very raspy, labored kind of
breathing which worked well here.
In order to have drama
that you care about,
there has to be something
underlying serious about it...
that's, you know,
a real threat to someone.
But on the other hand,
there's cartoon issues in it,
which is somebody can fall
from a high place and not get hurt...
or jump an incredible distance...
when at other times they can't run fast
enough to get away from something.
You know. It's filled with
these kind of dramatic ironies...
that one has to be really careful
about how you balance them.
LUCAS: I would never have made
Empire Strikes Back the way I did...
if I wasn't absolutely confident
I was gonna be able to make
Return of the Jedi.
Because to make a movie
with no beginning
and no end was a huge risk...
and wouldn't work, really,
unless there was the third film...
to put it together
and make this into a trilogy...
so that you could actually
follow the whole story.
MUREN: In this tunnel model,
the biggest opening...
was probably a foot across,
and then it would go off...
another foot or two on either side
with the different struts
and everything holding it up.
And the big area here in the end
was a really nice model that was-
I think it was-I remember it about
being 10 feet across or so.
The big thing in the middle was
probably about four or five feet across-
the big dome thing that's hanging
from the ceiling that crumbles.
So it was a pretty good scale.
The explosions added later onto it.
Being chased by the fireball
was a pretty exciting thing...
that Richard worked on
and a lot of the pyro guys...
to get that sense of fire coming
right toward you
but never quite
catching up with you-
which is a difficult thing to do
because fire just wants to overtake you.
So they were pulling the camera back
at the same time...
as a fireball was actually coming toward
the camera to get these elements here.
And they actually built some of it
actually in a real model.
It wasn't even a combined explosion
or fire. It was actually in the model.
Probably the model, in those cases,
would only work for one take I think.
And a final massive explosion,
huge scale,
shot separately from
the actual Death Star itself.
BURTT: As we got further along
the editorial style
got much more rapid.
That is, the shots were shorter in length
and more of them packed together.
The challenge for sound editing
and sound design is always related to...
how many cuts there are in the movie,
how rapidly it goes from shot to shot.
Because essentially,
every time there's a cut in a movie...
there's perhaps a necessity
to change the sound.
Either introduce a new sound
or modify another one...
at the same rate that
you're seeing imagery change.
So the quicker the cuts,
the more effort there has to be...
in careful consideration as to how
you change the sound on every cut.
Because, you know,
do you have something overlap
and hang over into the next shot,
do you precede
a cut with another sound,
do you have a different sound
on every cut,
and if you do, will it just sound
like a bunch of bumps,
brief moments of sound
that are just a burst of noise?
It's so quick,
you can't tell what it is.
These are all really significant issues
when you are doing the sound design...
and trying to imagine
what the sounds are going to be...
and it's not only a matter
of coming up with the sounds...
but also sounds that will
connect together.
Like music would connect.
Sound effects,
it's somewhat the same idea...
that you do have to consider
how things will be connected together.
LUCAS: This little scene
where he burns his father's body-
it wasn't originally in the script.
But I decided it gave
more closure in terms of...
Luke's relationship to his father
and letting go of his father...
even though later on, as we get
to the end of the movie...
as he joins the Force, he is able
to retain his original identity.
It's because of Obi-Wan and Yoda,
who learn how to do that,
how to join the Force at will
and then retain your identity.
But it was his identity as he was
when he died as Anakin Skywalker.
MUREN: These fireworks were actually
shot up here at Northern California.
We rented the firework company
and shot a bunch one night.
That was fun. Boy, all the stuff
you always wanted to see,
you could just ask them to do it
and they'd shoot it up...
and we had a couple cameras
shooting at various speeds to get them
and put them into the shots.
That was really cute.
I think the people driving by
on the freeway enjoyed it also.
So, massive crowds here
that are pretty spectacular.
It just really led the way to
these movies where you see...
huge amounts of people doing stuff,
huge amounts of characters in scenes.
The scale's way, way bigger than
anybody had been imagining before.
The Ewoks were shot big in the frame...
and then projected from behind
with a little projector...
onto a little screen
maybe three or four inches wide.
And the painting painted on glass.
And wherever
you wanted to see Ewoks,
you scraped the painting away...
and projected in the film
of the Ewoks that had been shot.
And, you know, with a few of those
holes and the Ewoks in the shots...
and a few other ones for flames-
projecting in flames-
you end up with a scene
that looks like you're in a forest...
looking at a bunch of Ewoks and-
you know, with torches.
And it's all a big ol' fake.
But pretty neat-lookin'.
BURTT: Since the original Jedi,
we've added Coruscant, the emperor-
"Down with the emperor"
and all the people
toppling statues and things.
We've added Naboo,
which is Padmé's home,
and we've added Bespin,
which was Sky City.
The idea being
relating intergalactic celebration,
reviewing all the places
that we had been.
LUCAS: Star Wars was one of those
things that happens to you in life.
But it ended up taking over my life
and I ended up...
spending the next 30 years
making these films.
I love the films, but it's quite a bit
of commitment to your life,
I'll tell you, when you get down
to the day-to-day struggle.
[LAUGHS]