...happening outside the walls.
Tonight's storm is causing
all kinds of problems around the Bay.
Pete Giddings will have the forecast
and will show you
what would happen to the Bay
if some scientists' predictions come true.
All on 7 at 11:00.
What has 12 million eyes,
192 million teeth,
and stretches from the Golden Gate Bridge
all the way to the Twin Towers?
It's Hands Across America,
a 4,000-mile-long chain of Good Samaritans
standing hand in hand
through fields of grain,
past purple mountains,
and across fruited plains,
from sea to shining sea.
That's right.
This summer, six million people
will tether themselves together
to fight hunger in the United States.
Visit your local record shop
to find out how you can be a part
of Hands Across America.
Put some heat on that one.
Yeah, I guess
I missed my chance to go pro.
Oh!
Tell you what.
Right now, you could walk away
with a prize from the second level,
or you could keep going
for a prize from the third level.
Okay. What do you think, Addy?
Should we stop or keep going?
Don't look at me. It's your birthday.
I want number 11.
- Yeah?
- That one?
- Yeah.
- All right.
Uh, yeah. Uh, that one.
- Thanks, man.
- Of course.
Yeah.
That shirt better not give her nightmares.
In trouble for winning
my daughter a T-shirt.
That's a new one.
She was terrified
when it came on TV.
You'd know that if you were around,
all right?
Who let her watch it?
You know... You know,
they're filming something by the carousel.
You should see if
they're looking for extras.
Ah... I need another beer.
- Hmm.
- I can't have a beer now?
Hey. How about the Big Dipper?
Addy, do you want to try it?
Russel, you know
she's not big enough to do that.
And I sure as hell am not doing it, so...
Whac-A-Mole!
Yeah, Whac-A-Mole, guy.
That's what I'm talking about.
- How many tickets?
- Two tickets.
Two tickets.
Two tickets!
- Hey, Addy, come to the bathroom.
- I don't have to go.
Russel?
Russel!
Can you watch your daughter, please?
I'm watching.
Baby, stay close, okay?
- Glen.
- What?
- Stop it.
- I'm not doing anything.
- You keep doing scissors.
- I'm not.
I'm just cruising. Come on.
Um... What?
- This is ridiculous.
- Too rad.
- Come on, now.
- What?
- This is impossible.
- Oh, my God.
Don't do it. Don't do it.
These, the earth and water,
he divided into places
from which life could spring.
The mountains and the valleys
and the waters
were all where they should be.
Then Sotuknang went to Taiowa and said...
"I want you to see what I have built.
And I have done well."
And Taiowa looked and said,
"It is very good.
But you are not done with it.
Now you must create life of all kinds
and set it in motion according to my plan.
The universal plan."
And went into the endless space
and gathered substance
to create his helper,
the Spider Woman.
"Look all about you, Spider Woman,"
said Sotuknang.
"Here now is endless space.
But in the world,
there is no joyful movement.
The world needs... "
♪ Sometimes a mystery ♪
♪ Sometimes I'm free ♪
♪ Depending on my mood or my attitude ♪
♪ Sometimes I wanna roll or stay at home ♪
♪ Walking contradiction
Guess I'm factual and fiction ♪
♪ I'm always left of center ♪
♪ And that's right where I belong ♪
♪ I'm the random... ♪
We made it!
- Why?
- Dad!
- 'Cause y'all sleep too much.
- My God.
Come on. Let's go.
- Careful. Hey!
- See ya, wouldn't wanna be ya!
- Whatever.
- Bags in the house first.
Look.
- Ew.
- Come on.
You're too old.
- You know the drill.
- Don't judge me.
Don't judge me.
- Little dude.
- The Wi-Fi's not working.
You don't need the Internet.
You got the Outernet.
Good one.
Okay, okay. Knock, knock.
- Who's there?
- You.
- You who?
- Yoo-hoo.
Open up the door.
My God, what's wrong with you?
- Can we get a dog?
- No, we can't.
- You should run while you're here.
- Jason, eat something.
- Something.
- What?
- What's with all the attitude?
- For me.
I'm sorry. Yay, track and field.
Whoa. You don't want to run anymore?
You love track and field.
- Well, what's the point?
- The Olympics.
I'm not gonna make it to the Olympics.
You could do anything
you set your mind to.
- Can I drive while we're up here?
- No.
That's what I set my mind to.
- You know...
- Where you going, Jason?
- I'm gonna get something.
- You need to come and finish your food.
Cara and Haley drove
with parent supervision.
Well, you don't need to know how to drive
when you're an Olympic-caliber athlete.
- Oh, my God.
- You run.
You should run on the sand.
- Why?
- Because it's harder, okay?
No traction.
Practice on the beach,
you get on dry land, you take off.
We're going to the beach?
Yeah.
Well, later, once we get settled.
What beach?
Santa Cruz.
Josh, Kitty and the girls
are gonna be there.
What are you doing?
It's a magic trick.
I left it here last year.
Okay. Let's see it.
This thing's kind of bullshit.
Hey.
What, are we cursing at the table now?
When you point a finger at someone else,
you have three pointing back at you.
What is that supposed to mean?
It's four fingers pointing back at you.
- What are you talking...
- Look. See?
One's a thumb,
and it's not pointing at you.
So, what is it?
I think she has
post-traumatic stress disorder.
She wasn't in 'Nam.
Okay? She got lost. For 15 minutes.
- That's...
- That can be very scary.
You don't know what happened to her.
Anything could've happened to her.
Okay, so how... how do we get her to talk?
Look, I think we need to encourage her
to draw, to write, to dance.
Anything to help her tell us her story.
I just want my little girl back.
It's gonna be okay.
Um...
I need to have a smoke.
I don't get why we have a summer home
by the beach and don't go to the beach.
What about the beach right here?
- What beach?
- There's a beach right there.
That is not a beach.
That is a bay. That is a shore.
I'm talking about a real beach
with people and sand, amusement park.
There's, like... It's crowded there.
And, like,
there's weirdos at that beach and...
I... I'm not going to that beach.
- We're not going.
- Okay.
I guess I'll just cancel then.
Okay.
It just sucks, is all.
I mean, I know Jason
really was looking forward to it.
This is the first summer
we've been back here since Grandma died.
I know it's been pretty hard on him.
We leave before dark.
Yeah.
Yes. Yes.
It's gonna be great.
And you're gonna enjoy it.
- Mm-hmm.
Mm-hmm...
- Are you really not gonna kiss me?
- Mm-mmm.
You're not gonna kiss me? Hmm?
Where's your brother?
Your brother, where is he?
I don't know.
Really?
Jason?
Mom!
Baby, that's why you can't play in here.
- Didn't this happen last year?
- Zora, please.
Yeah!
That's right. What do you think?
Daddy is home, baby!
Craw Daddy! Ha ha!
- He's kidding, right?
- He is not kidding.
Got a cassette player and everything.
Leather seats!
Glove compartment!
Wow.
That's right.
It's even got one of these, baby!
Oh, I got it.
Guy taught me how to do this.
It veers a little to the left,
so you gotta hold on to it.
At least I got it really cheap.
- Will we all fit though?
- You know what?
Y'all are spoiled.
Spoiled.
Did you know there's fluoride in the water
that the government uses
to control our minds?
I forgot.
Nobody cares about the end of the world.
Maybe you could tell us
what's supposed to happen,
and then we can picture it.
Maybe you can kiss my anus, Zora.
- Ew!
- Whoa!
- What?
- "Anus" isn't a cuss word.
- Why are we even talking about anuses?
- Why would you say that?
I would have actually preferred
you use a curse word in this case.
- Mom, I can see you laughing.
- I am not laughing.
Where'd you even learn that?
Okay, we don't always have to be talking.
♪ I got more growing pains than Maggie ♪
♪ 'Cause homies nag me
To take the dank out of the baggie ♪
- ♪ I got five on it ♪
- ♪ Five on it ♪
- ♪ Got it good ♪
- ♪ Grab your 40... ♪
That's a classic right there.
- ♪ I got five on it ♪
- ♪ Five on it ♪
♪ Messin' with that Indo weed... ♪
What does "I got five on it" mean?
- It's about drugs.
- It's not about drugs.
It's a dope song. Don't do drugs.
- Jason, come on.
- Hmm?
Get in rhythm.
♪ Don't need no crutch
I'm so keyed up... ♪
There you go.
♪ Next time I'll roll it in a Hampa
To burn slow ♪
♪ So the ashes won't be
Burning up my hand, brah ♪
♪ Hoochies can hit ♪
♪ But they know they got to pitch in ♪
♪ Then I roll a joint
That's longer than your extension ♪
♪ 'Cause I'll be damned
If you get high off me for free ♪
♪ Hell no... ♪
Oh, yeah.
Welcome to Santa Cruz.
♪ 'Cause you know you got asthma ♪
- ♪ Crack a 40 open, homie, and guzzle it ♪
- Huh?
♪ 'Cause I know the weed in my system
Is gettin' lonely ♪
♪ I gotta take a whiz test to my PO ♪
♪ I know I failed 'cause... ♪
Santa Cruz!
- Santa Cruz!
- Okay, we get it!
Santa Cruz!
Santa Cruz! Santa Cruz!
- She did...
- Five minutes. You can't even talk.
I don't want to talk about who
can't talk. What's gonna happen?
- If something happened to her...
- What's gonna happen? She left!
Oh, my God.
- Don't look. Don't look.
- Is he dead?
You gotta be kidding me.
Hey.
Hey! What's up?
Thought you guys said 2:30.
Where's the efficiency?
- Us Wilsons, you know, we take our time.
- Hey.
- Hey. Look at you.
- Oh, my God.
- Welcome to paradise.
- Of course. Hey.
You look so pretty!
The girls are gonna be
so happy to see you.
- I got some beer for you.
- Becca! Lindsey!
- No.
- Look who's here!
- The answer is no.
- He's old enough.
- Give me a couple more years.
- Don't hog her.
Hi.
- No shit. You got the boat?
- Yep. I got the boat.
- Good for you, dude.
- Boom.
- That's fucking awesome. You get a dinghy?
- Shut up.
You got to make sure
you have the essentials.
- You got the life preservers?
- Got that.
- You got a fire extinguisher?
Do you have a flare gun?
I knew you'd fucking forget the flare gun.
We gotta get out there
to do a double excursion.
We're right across the bay
from you guys, for fuck's sake.
Sure you don't want anything to drink?
- No, I'm good. Thanks.
- This rosé is delicious.
Mm-hmm. I'm sure, yeah.
- Did you guys have a good summer so far?
- Yeah, it's been great.
A little bit small,
but a classic design, you know?
- You good?
- Yeah.
What?
I have a hard time just,
you know, talking.
Oh, I get that.
Yeah, no, I totally get that.
You guys, uh, want something?
Got a full bar here.
No. All good. Water.
You want thirds, huh?
- Thank you.
- Okay.
I'm gonna get my wife her medicine.
That's beautiful, isn't it?
- Here you go. Ah-ah.
- Oh, yeah.
What do we say?
I hate you?
- That works.
- Yeah? Good.
Never stops.
I think about murdering him sometimes.
- So nothing's changed, huh?
- Nope.
Ooh. Actually,
a little something has changed.
Oh, my God.
Did you get something done?
Just, like, an itsy-bitsy little thing.
- Fuck off.
- Yeah.
Well, you look just like
you did last year.
Aw, thank you.
I mean, that's the idea, you know.
Just, like, a little bit
can go a long way.
- Mmm.
- Not that you need anything, whore.
- Oh, man.
- Oops.
- What was it?
- Just a stupid tunnel. That's all.
Beach toys are such baby shit.
Your brother's so weird.
He just has a hard time focusing.
Are you going in the water?
- No.
- Why not?
- Yeah, why not?
- Hey, where are you going?
To the bathroom.
Why don't you pee in the ocean?
Jinx. Double jinx. Triple jinx. Blackout.
- Shut up.
- You shut up.
Do you ever wish you kept dancing?
- Try it.
- Sooner rather than later.
Sometimes, yeah.
'Cause you were, like...
you were really good, right?
Yeah, well.
I peaked at 14.
Oh, I mean, didn't we all?
I think I could have been a movie star
if the girls hadn't been born
at exactly the wrong time.
I went to Stella Adler.
And I booked two commercials
before I met Josh.
It's just, I stopped auditioning
when I got pregnant.
Then the move to San Francisco
was a career killer, and...
I was supposed to keep flying back to LA.
It's just...
Jesus. Watch it.
That's crazy.
Been having so many
crazy coincidences lately.
Yeah, that's what he said.
- We should go back to our place.
- Sure.
- I think it's vodka o'clock.
- Oh, yeah. Definitely.
- Okay, good. Let's pack up.
- Okay.
Where's Jason?
Mmm...
Jason. Where's Jason?
Gabe. Where's Jason?
Jason?
- Jason?
- Jason!
- Where were you?
- I was at the bathroom.
No! You don't do that.
- You don't run off without telling me.
- Ow!
I'm sorry.
Okay, okay. We're all good.
- We're good. All right.
- You don't do that to me.
- Understand?
- Sorry.
I'm gonna get ready to go.
I think we're gonna head out.
- Yeah.
- Okay?
- No worries.
- Yeah.
The Houston Astros were essentially short
one everyday player
heading into the season.
You saw their new car, right?
He had to do it. He just had
to get that thing to fuck with me too.
I guess mission accomplished.
Don't run inside.
Way to freak Mom out.
And here's something
you don't see every day:
extra innings in Minnesota.
I'm gonna go say good night.
11-11, tied in the seventh inning.
Yeah, you see, Hollister,
known for his late-inning fastball,
comes in at a cool...
You good?
I'm just gonna watch
the Giants highlights, okay?
I'll see you later in the magic room.
Night night.
- Good night.
- Phone off.
Mask off.
You thought I was dead?
Um... No, I just...
I just didn't know
if you were lost or taken or...
By terrorists and perverts?
Stick with me,
and I'll keep you safe, okay?
Look.
11:11.
Bedtime.
Who's this?
You know, I was thinking about
getting some fishing gear tomorrow.
Four rods.
We could all go fish off the dock.
You know?
Of course, there's the boat too.
I'm just saying,
if we could get out there in open water...
I'm not trying to force anyone.
Hey.
Gabe, I want to go.
- Where you trying to go?
- I can't be here, I...
It's too much.
You serious?
Being here, it, um...
Mmm...
It feels like there's this, um...
black cloud just hanging over me.
And, uh...
I don't feel like myself.
I think you look like yourself.
Okay. Yeah.
When I was a kid...
I went to that boardwalk with my parents.
I wandered off.
I don't know why. I just did.
I ended up in that hall of mirrors.
There was another girl in there.
She looked like me.
Exactly like me.
- But you were in the hall of mirrors...
- She wasn't a reflection.
She was real.
She...
I ran as fast as I could.
My whole life, I've...
I've felt like she's still coming for me.
Okay, well, whatever happened,
happened a long time ago, right?
You know how sometimes things line up?
- Yeah.
- You know, like coincidences.
Since we've been here,
they've been happening more and more.
I think... I feel like it means,
like, she's getting closer.
Who? The mirror girl?
You don't believe me.
I do. I do.
I'm... I'm processing. Okay?
I just...
can't believe
you kept all this inside for so long.
You know I'm here, right?
I'm pretty sure I could kick your ass,
so if she looks like you, then...
Okay. Bad joke.
All right. I'm sorry. My bad.
I'm just trying to lighten the mood.
Oh, shit.
We lost power. Perfect timing.
See, this is why
Josh has a backup generator.
God!
Jesus!
Okay, we lost power. Go back to bed.
There's a family in our driveway.
There is not a family in our driveway.
Huh.
Who is that?
Uh-uh.
It is a family.
What, y'all scared of a family?
A bogeyman's family.
Okay, all right. Enough... Enough of that.
- Uh-uh.
- Hey, hey.
- What?
- Zora, give me your phone.
- I'm not on it.
- Zora!
Sorry.
Is there someone outside?
It's just a family standing outside.
It's probably the neighbors.
- You're kidding me, right?
- Hello.
- I'm scared.
- My name is Adelaide Wilson.
- Are you seriously calling 911 right now?
- We're at 2311 Seagull Way. Shh!
- Everything's good. We lost power.
- There are trespassers on our property.
- All right, sure, okay.
- Yes.
- You know what?
- What?
- I'm gonna fix this.
- No, we don't.
- I'm gonna find out who they are...
- What? No, but I know they will.
...find out what they want,
and everything's gonna be fine.
Calm down, okay?
Fifteen minutes? No, that's too long.
- Oh, boy.
- No, you don't understand.
How about we all just try to keep calm.
- Gabe.
- Dad.
Everything's gonna be all right.
No, no. Wait. Just one sec. Gabe!
Trying to have a vacation.
My whole family lost they goddamn minds.
Hi. Can I help you?
Okay.
If y'all are out here
trying to scare people,
I think you picked
the wrong house for that.
Zora.
Put your shoes on.
I... I asked you nice.
Now I need y'all to get off my property.
Okay.
Okay, let's call the cops.
I did. They're 14 minutes away.
What? 14 minutes?
Okay, okay.
Okay. Jason, give me the bat.
- What bat?
- The baseball bat. The bat.
- There's one in the... Thank you.
- Here.
- Gabe?
- All right, hold on.
- I got this. Let's try this again.
- Gabe.
No, no.
All right.
- Gabe!
- I got this. I got this.
Now, I thought I already done told y'all
to get off my property.
Okay? So, if y'all want to get crazy,
we can get crazy.
Now, the cops are already on they way.
Hey. Hey!
Hey!
They're going around.
Is the back door locked?
- My window's open.
- Zora, no!
Gabe, Jason!
I'm serious, man!
I will break your head!
If I were you...
Gabe.
- The key.
- What key?
- The damn hide-a-key.
- Hide-a-key?
What kind of white shit...
Oh, shit.
- Mom?
- Just stay close.
What's going on?
What?
It's us.
We don't have anything here.
This is our summer home.
- Gabe.
- We just got in today, so...
Once...
upon...
a time...
there was a girl.
And the girl had a shadow.
The two were connected,
tethered together.
When the girl ate,
her food was given to her warm and tasty.
But when the shadow was hungry,
she had to eat rabbit,
raw and bloody.
On Christmas...
the girl received wonderful toys,
soft and cushy.
But the shadow's toys
were so sharp and cold,
they'd slice through her fingers
when she tried to play with them.
The girl met a handsome prince
and fell in love.
But the shadow,
at that same time,
met Abraham.
It didn't matter if she loved him or not.
He was tethered to the girl's prince,
after all.
Then the girl had her first child,
a beautiful baby girl.
But the shadow...
she gave birth to a little monster.
Umbrae was born laughing.
The girl had a second child,
a boy this time.
They had to cut her open
and take him from her belly.
The shadow had to do it all...
herself.
She named him Pluto.
He was born to love fire.
So, you see, the shadow hated the girl
so much for so long.
Until one day, the shadow realized
she was being tested by God.
Excuse me.
What do you want?
You could have my wallet.
You could have the car.
Gabe.
You could have the boat, for all I care.
Nobody wants the boat, Dad.
How about this? You take me to the ATM...
What are you people?
We're Americans.
Tether yourself to the table.
- Addy, don't do it.
- Maybe I should cut something off of you.
It's... It's okay.
Just...
don't hurt my children.
Yo.
Hey, hey. Get your hands off me.
- Hey!
- Wait.
Get off me, man.
Wait. Gabe.
Oh! Please, please stop!
- Stop, please!
- Gabe!
Stop, stop. Wait. Wait.
Okay. Okay.
- Mom.
- Little girl.
Run!
Go.
You want me, right?
No.
- He's not going.
- Careful.
He has a temper.
No, no, no.
Not that shit.
No. No.
Okay.
- I'm scared.
- Look. Look at me.
You're gonna be okay.
Show him one of your tricks.
Okay.
Go play, boys.
Don't burn our house down.
Stop, man.
Please stop.
No. Stop, stop.
Please. Come on, man, stop.
Stop it.
- I got a family, man.
- Please don't. No.
What the fuck?
Get off my car!
Are you... Come here. Come...
Goddamn it, get your ass over here.
I said come here.
Kid, I'm talking to you.
What do you want?
What?
What do we want?
We want to take our time.
We've been waiting for this day...
for so long.
I call it...
the Untethering.
That's yours.
It hangs to the left.
It hangs to the goddamn left.
Jason.
Baby. Come on. Come on.
Let's go.
Keys.
- Mom! Mom!
- Zora!
This way. Come on! Go, go!
Hey!
Come on, come on.
Oh, let's go, let's go!
Josh? What was that?
- What?
- I heard something outside.
Okay.
A rustling. Walking, like a person.
There's a person walking around
outside our fucking house.
It's probably a squirrel. I don't know.
Would you please get up and look?
I'm busy. I'm... I'm busy.
So...
Maybe it's a pizza guy.
Maybe the girls ordered pizza.
Get up and take a look. I'm scared.
Oh... I don't want to.
I want to stay down here.
I want to just stay in my cozy spot.
- Get up and look.
- Jesus Christ.
Hey, Ophelia, lights up.
Turning lights up.
I feel like I heard
the backup generator go on too.
What do you know
about the backup generator?
Can you stop being an asshole
for two seconds? Just look.
All right. I'm looking.
I'll get my binoculars.
I see nothing. I see beautiful stars.
- Are you really looking?
- Yeah, I'm looking.
Oh, shit. No, yeah, I...
There's something out there.
- Don't fuck with me, Josh.
- I'm not fucking with you. I'm serious.
There's something out there.
Look. Look behind the car.
- Where? I don't see it.
- It's by the car. Look.
I can't...
- Oh, shit.
- What?
Oh, my God, it's OJ.
It's OJ Simpson.
What is wrong with you? Seriously.
Ophelia, give me some Beach Boys.
- Really?
- Why not?
It's our last night here.
- Let's have a little party.
- Ophelia, turn it down.
Turning down
"Good Vibrations" by the Beach Boys.
Would you chill out.
There's nobody out there.
Go back upstairs.
I'll be up in a few minutes.
- Everything's gonna be fine.
- What's going on?
Uh, nothing.
- Nothing, guys.
- Jesus.
The backup generator went on.
We're just trying to figure it out.
Go back to sleep.
Just because we're in our rooms
doesn't mean we're sleeping.
Fine. I don't know. Go back to your rooms.
Guys, we have to be out of here
at 10:00 a.m. tomorrow, sharp, so...
♪ Good vibrations... ♪
- Hello?
- Oh, my God.
Josh!
- ♪ Good, good, good, good vibrations ♪
- ♪ She's giving me excitations ♪
- ♪ Excitations ♪
- ♪ Good, good, good ♪
- ♪ Good vibrations ♪
- ♪ She's giving me excitations ♪
- ♪ Excitations ♪
- ♪ Close my eyes ♪
♪ She's somehow closer now ♪
♪ Softly smile, I know she must be kind ♪
♪ When I look in her eyes ♪
♪ She goes with me to a blossom world ♪
♪ I'm picking up good vibrations ♪
♪ She's giving me excitations ♪
- ♪ Good vibrations ♪
- ♪ She's giving me excitations ♪
- ♪ Excitations ♪
- ♪ Good, good, good ♪
- ♪ Good vibrations ♪
- ♪ She's giving me excitations ♪
- ♪ Excitations ♪
- ♪ Good, good, good ♪
- ♪ Good vibrations ♪
- ♪ She's giving me excitations ♪
♪ Excitations... ♪
Please stop.
Stopping "Good Vibrations"
by the Beach Boys.
Ophelia...
Ophelia, call the police.
Sure. Playing "Fuck tha Police" by NWA.
♪ Fuck the police
Comin' straight from the underground ♪
♪ A young nigga
Got it bad 'cause I'm brown ♪
♪ And not the other color so police... ♪
♪ They have the authority
To kill a minority ♪
♪ Fuck that shit, 'cause I ain't the one ♪
♪ For a punk motherfucker with... ♪
Josh, we need your help.
♪ And thrown in jail ♪
♪ We can go toe-to-toe
In the middle of a cell ♪
♪ Fuckin' with me 'cause I'm a teenager ♪
♪ With a little bit of gold... ♪
Addy!
No!
Go, go. Run.
Come here! Huh?
Follow me!
Yeah.
Let's go, Bad Josh!
Let's go!
Hey!
♪ It's gonna be a bloodbath ♪
♪ Of cops dyin' in LA ♪
♪ Yo, Dre, I got somethin' to say ♪
♪ Fuck the police ♪
♪ Fuck, fuck, fuck the police ♪
♪ Example of scene one ♪
♪ Pull your goddamn ass over right now ♪
♪ Aw, shit, now what the fuck
You pullin' me over for? ♪
♪ 'Cause I feel like it ♪
♪ Just sit your ass on the curb
And shut the fuck up ♪
♪ Man, fuck this shit ♪
♪ A'ight, smart-ass
I'm taking your black ass to jail ♪
♪ MC Ren, will you please
Give your testimony to the jury ♪
♪ About this fucked-up incident... ♪
No! No!
♪ Because the niggas
On the street is a majority ♪
♪ A gang is with whoever I'm steppin' ♪
♪ And the motherfuckin' weapon
Is kept in a stash spot ♪
♪ For the so-called law ♪
♪ Wishin' Ren was a nigga
That they never saw ♪
♪ Lights start flashin' behind me ♪
♪ But they're scared of a nigga
So they mace me to blind me ♪
♪ But that shit don't work
I just laugh ♪
♪ Because it gives 'em a hint
Not to step in my path ♪
♪ For police, I'm sayin'
"Fuck you, punk" ♪
♪ Read my rights and shit ♪
♪ It's all junk ♪
♪ Pullin' out a silly club
So you stand ♪
♪ With a fake-ass badge
And a gun in your hand ♪
♪ But take off the gun
So you can see what's up ♪
♪ And we'll go at it, punk
And I'ma fuck you up ♪
♪ Make you think I'ma kick your ass ♪
♪ But drop your gat
And Ren's gonna blast ♪
♪ I'm sneaky as fuck
When it comes to crime ♪
♪ But I'ma smoke 'em now
And not next time ♪
♪ Smoke any motherfucker that sweats me ♪
♪ Or any asshole that threatens me ♪
♪ I'm a sniper with a hell of a scope ♪
♪ Takin' out a cop or two
They can't cope with me ♪
♪ The motherfuckin' villain that's mad ♪
♪ With potential to get bad as fuck ♪
♪ So I'ma turn it around
Put in my clip ♪
♪ Yo, and this is the sound ♪
♪ Yeah, somethin' like that... ♪
♪ Fuck the police ♪
♪ Fuck, fuck, fuck the police ♪
♪ Yeah, man, what you need? ♪
- ♪ Police, open up ♪
- ♪ Aw, shit ♪
♪ We have a warrant for Eazy-E's arrest ♪
♪ Get down and put your hands
Where I can see 'em... ♪
Come on!
Ah! Goddamn it.
No, no. Please.
No, no.
No! No.
No, Zora. No!
No! Please, please.
No! No!
No, please, no!
No, no, no.
♪ Creep on it, on it, on it, on it ♪
♪ Whoa, see, I'm ridin'
Higher and higher ♪
♪ Whoa ♪
- ♪ Kinda broke so ya... ♪
- It was unlocked.
Boats are done.
I am done with boats.
♪ Light anotherjoint like Cypress Hill ♪
♪ I steal doobies, spit loogies ♪
♪ When I puff on it
I got some bucks on it ♪
♪ But it ain't enough on it... ♪
I can't believe they're dead.
Why are they doing this?
I'm sorry, but all
of our operators are busy at the moment.
Please hold,
and the next available operator...
It's all just craziness.
I'm sorry, but all of our operators
are busy at the moment. Please...
How does 911 keep you on hold
all night long?
I just don't get it.
It's too many twins, man.
How many of everybody is there gonna be?
The boardwalk was ready to
close. A bunch of us had just gotten out.
And we were going to our cars
when the attack happened.
- Oh, shit.
- Don't curse.
I thought it was somebody
acting out, and then we saw red.
- You saw red?
- Yes, they were wearing red.
They didn't look right. They had scissors.
And they were just walking up to people
in the crowd and stabbing them.
You said they were stabbing people?
Yeah, it was chaos,
and then we... we just started running.
- Where did they come from?
- What? I... I don't know.
Someone said that they were
coming from the sewers.
The sewers? Okay, how many are...
I'm sorry. I think they're coming...
Uh, ma'am?
Ma'am?
Um... Okay, uh, so we certainly hope
everything is okay there.
It's too early to say
what exactly is unfolding.
But it does appear we are in the midst
of a brutal and terrifying attack
by people who are being described as
wearing red, carrying scissors or shears,
and doing what can only be described as
wreaking havoc on folks...
And they look like us.
They don't even know that yet.
Okay, Chris,
I'm gonna cut you off.
- Okay.
- We have new images coming in here.
Here we see a man wearing red who...
Okay, this... this seems to be
a group of individuals
engaged in some sort
of demonstration or protest.
It's not clear at this time if or how
these people are connected to the attacks.
- What is that?
- That's them.
What are they doing?
I don't know, but that would take
a shitload of coordination.
So, obviously, if you have
children present watching us right now,
you should turn them away.
We aren't sure what is about to happen.
- We have to go.
- What? You're joking, right?
Zora, Jason, help your father.
She's trippin'. Where would we go?
- The police, right?
- No.
We need to move and keep moving.
We take the coast.
- We go to Mexico.
- Mexico?
Okay. Whoa.
Whoa.
We got everything we need here.
Food, water, backup generator.
We're as safe here
as we're gonna be anywhere.
Tell that to Josh and Kitty.
They're right here.
- You're scaring the kids.
- Too late.
They think like us.
They know where we are.
They won't stop
until they kill us or we kill them.
Then let's make some traps or something.
Like, some Home Alone type stuff.
That way, if she comes...
Tell me you did not just reference
Home Alone.
- You know what I'm talking about.
- Gabe.
They've been planning this.
They have the upper hand.
This is the time to run,
not to be sprinkling
Micro Machines on the floor.
- What are Micro Machines?
- What's Home Alone?
We're not going anywhere,
and that's final.
You don't get to make
the decisions anymore!
So...
does this mean we get their car?
Come on, come on.
Who's got the keys?
Come on.
- Let's go.
- Get in the car.
- I'm driving.
- No way.
I told her no.
Dad's leg is messed up. You're handcuffed.
- It's not safe. I'm driving.
- Zora, no.
I have the highest kill count
in the family.
You don't have the highest kill count.
- I killed both twins.
- Wrong. I just killed the second one.
I killed Kitty.
So that's one, one, one and two.
I killed two.
I killed myself and Josh, so...
It doesn't matter. Zora, get in the back.
- Look!
- No.
Oh, shit. Put the windows up.
Put the windows up.
Okay.
You're gonna want to back up.
- Buckle up.
- Huh?
- Zora!
- Oh! Whoa!
Where is she? Did I get her?
She's there, she's there! Jesus!
Okay.
Zora.
Careful.
Okay, you're going too fast!
She's dead now, right?
- What are you doing?
- Mom.
Where's she going? Wait! And she left.
Your mom left the car.
Shh, shh.
Shh.
Whoa.
Is that our car?
It's the one that looks like me.
- Shit.
- Whoa. Wh... What?
Stay in the car. Lock the doors.
What is she doing?
It's a trap.
Get out!
Please.
No.
No!
Jason? Jason!
Jason?
Jason!
No! No!
- Addy!
- Mom!
Here.
We can hide here.
- They probably got bandages and stuff.
- Okay.
Mom knows what to do.
Ah!
Look.
It's the line.
What is that,
some kind of fucked-up performance art?
Where is he?
How it must have been
to grow up with the sky.
To feel the sun, the wind, the trees.
But your people took it for granted.
We're human too, you know.
Eyes. Teeth.
Hands. Blood.
Exactly like you.
And yet...
it was humans...
that built this place.
I believe they figured out
how to make a copy of the body,
but not the soul.
The soul remains one, shared by two.
They created the Tethered
so they could use them
to control the ones above.
Like puppets.
But they failed,
and they abandoned the Tethered.
For generations,
the Tethered continued without direction.
They all went mad down here.
And then...
there was us.
Put some heat on that one.
Yeah, I guess
I missed my chance to go pro.
You remember?
We were born special.
- I want number 11.
- Yeah?
Addy, you want to try it?
God brought us together that night.
I never stop thinking about you.
How things could have been.
How you could have taken me with you.
Years after we met...
...the miracle happened.
That's when I saw God,
and he showed me my path.
You felt it too.
The end of our dance.
The Tethered saw that I was different,
that I would deliver them
from this misery.
I found my faith.
And I began to prepare.
It took years to plan.
Everything had to be perfect.
I didn't just need to kill you.
I needed to make a statement
that the whole world would see.
It's our time now.
Our time up there.
And to think,
if it weren't for you...
I never would have danced at all.
My baby. My baby.
I found you.
Oh!
Look. Look.
They're all gone now.
Okay?
They can't hurt you.
You understand?
Uh-uh.
Everything's gonna be like it was before.
Yeah.
She wasn't in 'Nam.
Okay? She got lost. For 15 minutes.
- That's...
- That can be very scary.
You don't know what happened to her.
- Anything could've happened to her.
- Okay, okay.
So how... how do we get her to talk?
Encourage her to draw,
to write, to dance.
Anything to help her tell us her story.
I just want my little girl back.
Okay? She left.
I told you to look after her.
- Yeah. Yeah.
- Look at you.
- It's not my fault she left.
It's not my fault she...
Yeah, well, look at me.
Look at you. Look at you!
♪ Will somebody wear me to the fair? ♪
♪ To the morning sings a lonely flower ♪
♪ Will a lady pin me in her hair? ♪
♪ Mm-hmm, hmm ♪
♪ Will a child find me by a stream? ♪
♪ Daylight will give a sunbeam shower ♪
♪ Kiss my petals ♪
♪ Weave me through a dream ♪
♪ For all of these simple things
And much more ♪
♪ A flower was born ♪
♪ It blooms to spread love and joy
Faith and hope ♪
♪ To people forlorn ♪
♪ Inside every man ♪
♪ Lives the seed of a flower ♪
♪ If he looks within ♪
♪ He finds beauty and power ♪
♪ Ring all the bells, sing
And tell the people everywhere ♪
♪ That the flower has come ♪
♪ Light up the sky
With your prayers of gladness ♪
♪ And rejoice, for the darkness is gone ♪
♪ Throw off your fears
Let your heart beat freely ♪
♪ At the sign that a new time is born ♪
♪ Mm-hmm, hmm ♪
♪ For all of these simple things
And much more ♪
♪ A flower was born ♪
♪ It blooms to spread love and joy
Faith and hope ♪
♪ To people forlorn ♪
♪ Inside every man ♪
♪ Lives the seed of a flower ♪
♪ If he looks within ♪
♪ He finds beauty and power ♪
♪ Ring all the bells, sing
And tell the people everywhere ♪
♪ That the flower has come ♪
♪ Light up the sky
With your prayers of gladness ♪
♪ And rejoice, for the darkness is gone ♪
♪ Throw off your fears
Let your heart beat freely ♪
♪ At the sign that a new time is born ♪