Out there, there’s a
world outside of Yonkers,
Way out there beyond
this hick town, Barnaby,
There’s a slick town, Barnaby.
Out there, full of shine
and full of sparkle,
Close your eyes and
see it glisten, Barnaby.
Listen, Barnaby!
Put on your Sunday clothes,
there's lots of world out there
Get out the brillantine and dime cigars
We're gonna find adventure
in the evening air
Girls in white in a perfumed night
Where the lights are bright as the stars!
Put on your Sunday clothes,
we're gonna ride through town
In one of those new
horse drawn open cars
We'll see the shows at Delmonico’s
And we'll close the town in a whirl
And we won't come home
until we've kissed a girl!
Too much garbage in your place?
There is plenty of space out in space!
BnL StarLiners leaving each day.
We'll clean up the
mess while you're away.
The jewel of BnL fleet, The Axiom.
Spend your 5 year cruising in style.
Maided on 24 hours a day
by our fully automated crew,
while your captain and auto pilot try
to course for non-stop entertainment.
Buy and dining.
And with our all access hover-chairs,
even grandma can join the fun.
There is no need to walk.
The Axiom, putting the star
in an executive StarLiner.
Because of BnL, space
is the final frontier.
...in your Sunday... No
Monday in your Sunday...
No Monday in your Sunday clothes!
Put on your Sunday clothes
when you feel down and out
Strut down the street
and have your picture took
Dressed like a dream your
spirits seem to turn about
That Sunday shine is a certain sign
That you feel as fine as you look!
...about
And we'll recall...
...when time runs out
That it only...
...took a moment
To be loved...
...a whole life long!
And that is all
That love's about
...took a moment
To be loved...
...a whole life long!
Hold me close and hold me fast
The magic spell you cast
This is La Vie En Rose
When you kiss me, Heaven sighs
And though I close my eyes,
I see La Vie En Rose
When you press me to your heart,
I'm in a world apart
A world where roses bloom
And when you speak
Angels sing from above
Every day words seem
to turn into love songs.
Cancel.
Why zone? Many? Are you monger?
Directive?
Ta-da!
Direc... tive?|
- Directive?
Classified!
Name?
Wa... Wall-E.
Wall-E?
Wall-E!
Eve.
E... |
- Eve!
E... A... |
Eve!|
- Eva.
Eva!
Eve.
Eva! Eva!
Wall-E...
Wall-E!
Eva!
Here is a little song I wrote
Sing it note for note... Don't worry
Be happy
Here.
Look.
Pop.
You pop.
An odd seem.
Where is Wall-E!
And that is all
That love's about
And we'll recall...
...when time runs out
That it only...
...took a moment
To be loved...
Eva!
...a whole life long!
Eva?
Eva!
E- E-
Eva.
Eva!
So let's go to over the driving range and
had a view of virtual race in the space.
Nah, we did that yesterday,
I don't wanna do that.
Well, then what do you wanna do?
- I do not know. Something.
- Make a place...
- He's jealous because...
- We've just sell...
- Look, I'm tired of...
If you can't full the stroll you
haven't seen the side any good.
A cup. Over here!
Buy N Large, everything
you need to be happy.
Your day is very important to us.
Come on! Here, take the cup.
Hey, take the cup!
Please remain stationary!
A service robot will be here
to assist you momentarily.
Stewards! Help!
Please remain stationary!
A service robot will be here
to assist you momentarily.
What's that? What’s going on?
Wall-E!
John.
- Eva?
- No. John.
Eva!
Bye, Wall-E.
A is for Axiom, your home sweet home.
B is for Buy N Large,
your very best friend.
Time for lunch, in a cup.
Feel beautiful!
- I'm studying right now.
- I know honey. Ah, men...
Attention, Axiom shoppers!
Try blue, it's the new red.
The date after we started to date...
...every hollow day to this
day has been a virtual disaster!
- Why he wasn't so superficial, you know?
- Yeah, I know my dear.
There's a lot of men out there.
Well, I know, I know
because I... What the?...
Wall-E!
- Mary.
- Eva!
Oh, oh, sure, go ahead.
Eva.
Shade!
I didn't know we had a pool!
Captain, you're needed at the bridge.
I'm at the deck!
Morning. |Just a trim?
Oh, I see. |I know honey, I know.
I'm good, I'm good, you look gorgeous.
- Sir.
- Coffee.
Sir...
Protocol, Auto. |First things first.
Computer! Status report.
- Mechanical systems?
- Unchanged.
- Reactor core temperature?
- Passenger count?
- Unchanged.
- The general food refill?
- Probe repair grounds?
- Unchanged.
- Atmosphere conditions?
- Conditions values?
- Unchanged.
- Ok, Auto.
- Sir, we have...
12:30? Auto, why didn't you wake
me for morning announcements?
Honestly, it's the one thing
that I can deal on this ship.
Well, good morning, everybody.
And welcome to the day
255,642 on board in the Axiom.
As always, weather is above
22 degrees and sunny and...
Oh, hey, I see the ship's log is showing
that today is our 700th anniversary...
...of our 5 year cruise. Well,
I'm sure our forefathers...
...would be proud to know
that 700 years later...
...we'll be doing the exact
same thing they were doing.
So, be sure next meal time
to ask for your free...
..."Sep tu a centennial" cup
cake in a cup! Well, look at that!
Also, today we have a...
Hey, hey, Auto, what’s
that flashing button?
Captain, probe Eve has
returned with positive.
Positive?
Eva!
But, no probes ever
come back positive...
...before.
Greetings and congratulations, captain!
If you are seeing this, that means your
Extraterrestrial Vegetation Evaluator...
...or EVE Probe has returned from
Earth with a confirm specimen...
...of on going photosynthesis.
That's right, it means
it's time to go back home.
Home? We're going back?
Now that Earth has been restored
to a life sustaining status...
...my buddy we can be get
up "Operation Recolonize".
Simply follow this manual's
instructions to place the plant...
...in your ship's holo-detector.
And the Axiom will immediately
navigate your return to Earth.
It's that easy!
But the effects of microgravity, you and
your passengers may have suffered some...
...slight bone loss.
But I'm sure a few laps around
in ship's jogging track...
...you'll get your back
in shape in no time.
We have a jogging track?
If you have any further questions,
just consult your operation manual.
See you back home, real soon!
Operate Manual.
Manual, relay instructions!
Manual!
Wow! Look at that!
Let's see!
Eva!
Wall-E!
Eva.
Well, let's open her up!
Step one. Voice command,
"Confirm acquisition".
Confirm acquisition.
Voice authorization required.
Uhh...
Accepted.
Whe... Where's the that thing?
- Plant!
- Plant, right, right.
Where is it?
Maybe we missed a step.
Let's look it again.
Ok.
Wall-E!
- Eva?
- Quiet!
Use your scanner to be sure.
Contains no specimen.
Probe's memory is faulty.
- So then we're not going Earth?
- Negative.
- I guess, things go back to normal, huh?
- Correct, captain.
Well, false alarm!
False Alarm.
Probe must be defective.
GO-4! Send it to repair ward.
And I have the one diagnostics
on her make sure she's not...
Wall-E!
Have Wall-E cleaned?
Eva!
Analyze!
Analysis. Foreign contaminant.
Substance is a three base system...
...composed various combinations
of natural derived elements.
Subject is most commonly refer
to as soil, dirt or Earth.
Earth?
Define "Earth".
Earth. The surface of the world
as distinct from the sky or sea.
Wow!
Define "sea".
Sea. An expensive salt water. They
covers most of the Earth surface...
...and surrounds it's continents.
Eva!
You look gorgeous!
Eve!
Clear! Clear! Clear!
Eva!
Wall-E!
Oh, my!
Halt!
Wall-E.
Caution! Rogue robots.
Wall-E!
Halt! Halt!
Caution! Rogue robots.
Wall-E!
Eva!
Eva?
Earth.
Earth!
Directive.
Wall-E.
Wall-E!
Plant!
Wall-E.
Eva!
Wall-E!
Cruising speed.
You are now creative movement in cabin.
Halt!
20 seconds to self destruct.
10 seconds to self destruct.
10, 9, 8, 7, 6...
5, 4, 3, 2...
No! No!
Eva!
Wall-E!
Eve!
- Wall-E. -
Wa... Wa... Wait.
Eva.
Wall-E!
Wall-E.
Oh, so many stars!
Hey! Hey, that's... |What's his name?
- Hey, what the...
- Look! Look, look, look!
Look at that!
Hey, I know that guy. |It's... Wall-E!
- That's him! Wall-E! Hey! It's
your buddy, John! - Hi, Wall-E.
Hi.
Define "hall down".
Hall down. A social gathering in
which lively dancing with take place.
Auto! This is amazing!
These are called farms!
Humans put seeds into the
ground, put water on them...
...and they grow food, like pizza.
Good night, captain.
Psst! Computer!
Define "dancing".
Dancing. A series of movements
involving two partners...
...with speed and rhythm
much harmoniously with music.
Eva.
The leader deck is now closing.
- Stop it!
- Make me.
I didn't know we had a pool.
No splashing, no diving.
No splashing... no...
Eva!
Directive!
A perfect landing!
We're here everybody!
Yeah, captain! Captain,
we're home. It's so beautiful!
No, it's nothing. I
- I was pleased to do this.
This is... This is all about
you people, not about me. It's...
How?
How did you found it?
We can go back home! For the first time!
What's it like now?
No, no, no! Don't tell me.
I want to see for myself.
Wait, that doesn't look like Earth.
Where's the blue sky?
Where's the grass?
Put on your Sunday clothes
when you feel down and out
I know that song.
They're... Uhmm...
Dancing. Yes, dancing.
You made somehow, huh, little guy?
You didn't give up, did you?
Oh, God!
Wait a minute!
...when time runs out
That it only...
Eva? Eva!
Wall-E.
Eva? Eva.
Eva?
Eva.
Eva!
There you go, little guy.
You came a long way
for a drink of water.
Just need someone who will
look after you, that's...
We have to go back!
Auto! Come down here.
Aye aye, sir.
Wall-E.
Wall-E?
Auto, Eve found the plant.
Fire up the holo-detector.
Not necessary, captain.
You may leave it to me.
You know what? I should do it myself.
Captain!
Sir, I insist you. |Give me the plant.
Auto, get out of my way!
- We can not go home.
- What are you talking about? Why not?
That is classified.
Captain, give me the plant.
What you mean classified? You don't
keep a secret from the captain.
- Give me plant!
- Why is that classified?
- Give me plant.
- Tell me, Auto. That's an order!
Aye aye, sir!
Dispatch.
Hey there, autopilots.
I've got some bad news.
Operation Cleanup
was... Well, uh, failed.
You know, raising toxics levels
made life unsustainable on Earth.
Unsustainable? What?
I'm afraid we gonna have to cancel
"Operation Recolonize". So...
...just stay the course. Uhmm... Rather
than trying to fix this problem...
...it will be just easier
for everyone remain in space.
Easier?
- Mr. President... Mr. President.
- But I think... Huh?
- Time to go!
- Ok! I'm giving override...
...a directive A113,
go to full auto pilot...
...take control of everything
and do not return to Earth.
Repeat, do not return to Earth!
Let's get the heck out of here.
Now, the plant.
No! Wait a minute!
Computer, when was that
message sent after to the Axiom?
Message received in the year 2110.
That's... That's nearly 700 years ago!
Auto, things have
changed! We gotta go back!
Sir, the orders are "Do
not return to Earth. "
But life is sustainable now.
Look at this plant! Green and growing.
It's living proof, he was wrong!
- Irrelevant, captain.
- What completely relevant?
Out there is our home. Home,
Auto! And it's in trouble.
I can't just sit here and do nothing.
That's all I've ever done!
That's all everyone in this
blasted ship has ever done!
Nothing!
Only in the Axiom you would be survive.
I don't want to survive! I want to live!
Just following my directive.
I am the captain of the
Axiom. We are going home today!
GO-4? Hey!
This is mutiny! Eve, arrest him!
Eve, you gonna put this plant
straight in the holo-detector.
No!
Eva?
- Wall-E
- Wall-E!
Eva!
- Throw the plant!
Throw it to me! - Wall-E!
Eva!
Give me the plant.
No!
Wall-E!
All communications are terminated.
- You're confined to your quarters.
- No!
Mutiny! Mutiny!
Wall-E?
Caution! Activating air-lock disposal.
Wall-E!
Activating air-lock disposal.
- Eve...
- Wall-E!
Caution! Activating air-lock disposal.
Activating air-lock disposal.
Wall-E!
Eve...
Wall-E.
M
- O.
- M-O?
- M-O.
M
- O.
Directive.
Directive!
Earth.
Earth!
Earth?
Earth.
Earth? Earth!
- M-O.
- Wall-E!
Wrong!
Please hold. We are currently having...
Eva!
Caution! Rogue robots.
Oh, that style suits you.
Clear.
Caution! Rogue robots.
Not possible!
Auto! Auto! Hear me!
You stupid wheel!
Caution! Rogue robots.
The plant!
We'll see who's powerless now!
Testing, testing. Is this thing on?
Hey, this is the captain.
I'm locked in my room.
Eve, Wall-E, bring the
plant to the leader deck.
Go back and activate the holo-detector.
Now, hurry! Auto is
probably gonna cut me...
Halt!
Oh, my!
Clear!
Halt! Halt!
- Look what I've got, Auto!
- Not possible.
That's right! The plant.
Oh, you want it? Come and get it blinky.
No!
Captain? Captain?
Let go!
- Let go!
- Too heavy for you?
You're not gonna get
away from me when I...
- Leave it, boss.
- Is that all you got?
Knock it off!
Halt!
- I insist. This is not good.
- Come closer. Gotcha!
Remain calm! Remain calm!
Ladies and gentlemen, this
is your captain speaking.
We've a slight malfunction
with the auto-pilot.
Please, remain calm.
Enough.
- Grab it!
- No! No, no, no! No!
- Grab on to me!
- Help me!
I got you!
John, get ready to have some kids!
Look out!
No!
Wall-E!
Auto!
Auto, you are relived of duty.
No...
Plant! Plant!
- Plant!
- Eva!
Plant origin verified.
Wall-E.
Course set for Earth.
10 seconds to hyper jump.
- 9, 8, 7, 6,
5... - No, Wall-E!
Oh, no, Wall-E...
4, 3, 2, 1, 0.
Wall-E!
Eva!
Wall-E.
Eve.
Wall-E?
Put on your Sunday clothes
when you feel down and out
Wall-E?
Wall-E, you're home!
Wall-E!
- Eva?
- Wall-E?
Eva?
And that is all...
...that love's about.
- Yeah! - Ok! -
Go, go. Go, go, go!
...when time runs out
This is called farming.
You kids are gonna grow
all kinds of plants!
Vegetable plants, pizza plants...
It's good to be home!
...a moment
To be loved...
...a whole life long!